<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mirrour of created perfection. Or The life of the most blessed Virgin Mary Mother of God. Written by the R. Fa. I.F. of the Society of Iesus</title>
            <author>Falconer, John, 1577-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 136 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 86 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00537</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10677</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117677</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852888</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852888</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18242</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00537)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18242)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 834:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mirrour of created perfection. Or The life of the most blessed Virgin Mary Mother of God. Written by the R. Fa. I.F. of the Society of Iesus</title>
                  <author>Falconer, John, 1577-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 46 [i.e. 146] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English College Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Permissu superiorum. 1632.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I.F. = John Falconer.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The life of the B. Virgin Mary.</note>
                  <note>some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary, --  Blessed Virgin, Saint --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18242:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18242:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE MIRROVR of Created Perfection.</p>
            <p>OR The Life of the moſt Bleſſed VIRGIN MARY Mother of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by the R. Fa. J. F. of the Society of</hi> IESVS.</p>
            <p>Permiſſu Superiorum. 1632.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18242:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18242:2"/>
            <head>TO THE VERTVOVS AND RELIGIOVS SISTER, AGNES ROSENDALE NOW CALLED Siſter <hi>Agnes</hi> of <hi>S. Albert,</hi> natiue of <hi>Brabant,</hi> &amp; Religious in the Monaſtery of Engliſh <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molites</hi> at <hi>Antwerpe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ODS gracious good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in calling you not only to a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious life in general, but to this particular Order, ſo eminently flouriſhing in Chriſts Church, &amp; very Houſe likewiſe where now you liue, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing
<pb facs="tcp:18242:3"/>it ſelf in the primitiue fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and exact obſeruance of your holy Mother <hi>S. Tereſa</hi> her Rule, to edify by your holy exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and help alſo by your tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall meanes poore Exiles, and Stra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers; ſeemeth equally to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue Gods fatherly care of them, and ſpeciall loue to your Selfe: clay ming withall thankefull reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects from their Engliſh friends, and from my ſelf in particuler, as hauing had the fauour affoarded me, of holding your Heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpouſe in my hands, whilſt by your Profeſſion, you eſpouſed your ſelfe ſo ioyfully, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly vnto him, as to me and others then preſent, the ioy of your Nuptialls, ſeemed to haue byn, in heauen, and in earth, ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated togeather.</p>
            <p>And indeed the diuine Author of your vocation ſeemed then to
<pb facs="tcp:18242:3"/>haue much pleaſed himſelfe, in beholding his Graces ſo effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in you, as it may wel be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whether you imbraced them more feruorouſly at firſt, or put them in executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more heroical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afterwards, when deafe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary perſuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of your worldly friends, and dexterouſly freed from that domeſticall, and vniuſt Captiuity, whereby they had for ſome moneths together, forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly reſtrayned you, getting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to the Monaſtery, and well aſſured, that the doore thereof would not, but with ſome bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter allowance of your powerfull friends, be opened to receaue you (as the Reuerend Mother &amp; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious of themſelues exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſired) with an heroicall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, ſcarcely to be exempli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, you pulled of your ſecular rich cloathes, put your ſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:18242:4"/>a ſmall Wheele, ſeruing (as the manner is) to take in and out things needfull for the incloſed, left at that tyme by a rare chance vnlocked, and ſo turned your ſelf into the place you deſired, by ſuch a ſtrange meanes, as it no leſſe amazed the Reuerend Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Siſters to ſee a perſon of your knowne quality, kneeling almoſt naked before them, with flowing teares begging their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly habit, then it ioyed your ſelfe to haue gotten in ſo among them.</p>
            <p>For ſurely to me, and others ſince, this entry of yours ſeemed almoſt miraculous, the ſtraytnes of the Wheele, deuided into foure parts, and your tall ſtature conſidered; the deuiſe at leaſt, &amp; your manner of executing it, was (I doubt not) diuinely ſuggeſted and not without a myſtery per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, as the Religious ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching
<pb facs="tcp:18242:4"/>the day after your profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in a great Auditory of your owne friends, and other princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall perſons, well noted, when as he tould them, that Chriſt in his ſpirituall eſpouſall of you, was pleaſed to obſerue in a ſort, what he had formerly commaunded to the Iewiſh Captaines, and ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diars, in marrying their beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full captiues, <hi>Deut.</hi> 21. by not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting you, captiued by loue vnto him, amongſt his other pure ſpouſes, there louely and beloued by him, but ſtripped firſt of ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar garments, and made ready to haue a holier Habit put vpon you, exteriourly courſe, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriourly gracing you, in the eyes and hart of your diuine Louer, with the hidden bewties of holy ſoules chiefly delighted: wherin, I dare ſay, you are not meane, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſuch as are excellent, ſo
<pb facs="tcp:18242:5"/>far, as an immaculate purity of mind and body, with an inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous candor of Nature, inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of Life, admirable Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and a continuall ardour of diuine loue, often interrupting, and hindring whole nights to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather, the needfull repoſe of your ſenſes, may argue deepe foundations laid of high buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings likely heereafter, by the heauenly Architect, to be rayſed in you, and his Bleſſed Mother, a continuall Leader and Helper of ſuch pure ſoules into the bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roome, and inmoſt bed-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of her ſonne, there to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced graciouſly by him.</p>
            <p>Wherfore I haue purpoſely heer collected her Life, a cleere Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour &amp; Rule of all perfection, as <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> calleth it, &amp; dedicated it, as a ſincere teſtimony of my Religious reſpect, vnto you, and
<pb facs="tcp:18242:5"/>that holy family; that Engliſh gentelwomen alſo, hapning by this occaſion to read this hiſtory of your exemplar Vocation to Religion, and feruourous proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution thereof (rather touched by me indeed, then fully related) may learne therby, how to leaue worldly friends, and temptations behind them, to enioy abroad, ſuch ſweet retyrements, &amp; ſtrait imbracings of their Heauenly Spowſe, as their owne Homes cannot now affoard them.</p>
            <p>Neither haue they to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, your Example alone, but the like alſo in many other emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Gentle-women of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who haue trampled ſecular Braueryes, neglected Worldly contentments and preferments, left their Country, and forſaken the delicacyes of their Parents houſes, to enter into ſeuerall Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteryes
<pb facs="tcp:18242:6"/>abroad, as into ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Bride-chambers of their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly ſpouſe, temporally firſt to ſerue, and eternally afterwards to enioy him; who lightneth his burden layd on them ſo by abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant graces, and ſweetneth his yoke by heauenly conſolations, as they feele not almoſt the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended auſterities of a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous life; but contrarily find ſuch a peacefull ſweetnes of conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, in the practiſe of them, as <hi>S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nards</hi> ſaying is truly verifyed in them, who ſpeaking of ſecular iudgments made concerning the paynefulnes of Religious diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, <hi>Cruces vident, conſolationes non agnoſcunt;</hi> they looke vpon our croſſes, but know not our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forts: this being (ſayth <hi>S. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi>) the difference, <hi>inter delicias cordis &amp; corporis</hi> between the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of the ſoule and the body,
<pb facs="tcp:18242:6"/>that theſe latter are veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, but by being experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced quickly come to be loathed: whereas contrarily the other, are dully apprehended, but deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully taſted, <hi>tanto<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>ue a comedente ampliùs eſuriuntur, quantò &amp; ab eſuriente ampliùs comeduntur,</hi> and by being more greedily eaten, they come to be more hungerly longed after: ſo as the Prophet biddeth vs firſt to taſt, and then to ſee, how ſweet God is, to his children and ſeruants.</p>
            <p>I may well ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke your ſelf amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the happy enioyers of ſuch hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly delights, ſince your liuing in that place hath byn as a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall ſitting at a full Table of them; &amp; auſterities there appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended indeed to be farre grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then young tender gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women in experience find them, haue (as I haue byn certaynely
<pb facs="tcp:18242:7"/>informed) byn no more felt by you, then bitter pills wrapped in ſugar, come to be taſted by ſuch as ſodainely ſwallow them.</p>
            <p>Shall I ſay (&amp; perchance truly) Gods gracious fauors to haue bin the greater towards you, for lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in a ſort your Country and friends, as your companions haue actually done theirs, by liuing ſo amongſt ſtrangers in it, as if you were quite out of it? If it be ſo, you are worthily to eſteeme (as to my knowledge you do) your pregnant Vocation to that Houſe, a ſingular grace of God; and your Admiſſion therein, a particuler fauour, commonly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by the Religious of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who are knowne in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to refuſe ſtrangers, albeit ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry worthy perſons, amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as I for my part therby conceaue the odour of their holy Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="tcp:18242:7"/>to be very ſweet, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to God, it being able ſo to attract ſtrangers, diuinely alſo guided, vnto them.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your deuoted poore Friend, and Seruant in Chriſt <hi>IESVS. I. F.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:18242:8"/>
            <head>The Authours Preface, to the B. Virgin.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Most pure, &amp; gracious Mother of my heauenly Redeemer; whilſt in theſe Papers, I haue ſought to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe thy Greatnes, I haue ſeemed to my ſelfe, as one ſayling, with a ſmall Cock-boat, in a vast Ocean, or labouring with ſingle ſandes, to rayſe a high mountayne: He indeed, knowing the least who thinketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe able to comprehend thee, Perfect in thy nature, Sacred in thy Office, Complete in thy Graces, and now Wonderfull in thy glorious Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; imitating thy Sonnes Vertues most, as being more, then all other Saintes, ſtored with his Goodnes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blest to ſee our neceſsityes, readyest to aske remedies for them, and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullest from him, who will deny thee
<pb facs="tcp:18242:8"/>nothing, to obtayne them.</p>
            <p>I offer heere, the ſlender fruites of my poore Prayers, to thy Selfe, the gracious ſubiect of them; ayming at no other end in them, then ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Deuotion towards thee, in ſuch, as shall read them. Which J aske alſo for my ſelfe, as a far greater bleſsing, then J can merit any wayes by them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:18242:9"/>
            <head>The Authours Petition.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>VAst Sea of Glory, who art bleſt</l>
               <l>With an Eternall Calme, rayſe in my brest</l>
               <l>Tempests of Sorrow, stormes of ſighes,</l>
               <l>Let waues of teares breake through myne eyes,</l>
               <l>That they may quench, ere life is done,</l>
               <l>The dreadfull wrath of thy deare Sonne.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18242:9"/>
            <head>THE LIFE OF THE BLESSED VIRGIN MARY.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>Of our Bleſſed Ladyes high, and holy Pedigree.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HOSE texts of the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Mother of God is mentioned, are not vnfitly, by a graue Authour, compared to deep grounds in muſicke, ſo cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly layd, as no diſcant of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane prayſes, can neerly expreſſe them.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:18242:10"/>
               <p> Her lineal diſcent from Dauid regiſtred by two of the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, and her being Coſin to <hi>S. Elizabeth</hi> (as the Angell called her) do ſufficiently aſſure vs, that her high and holy Pedigree was of Patriarchicall, Propheticall, Prieſtly, and Princely Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours iointly compoſed.</p>
               <p>Theſe foure ſortes of Perſons therein contayned, were as foure rootes, out of which, this flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing branche of <hi>Ieſſe</hi> his tree, happily iſſued.</p>
               <p>They were like to the foure Riuers flowing in Paradiſe, from whoſe cleare ſtreames, meeting togeather, this inundation, and full of ſea of heauenly graces (as we may rightly call this ſacred Virgin) was deriued.</p>
               <p>They were as foure Wheeles, on which this royall Chariot of Maieſty, and Loue, was brought
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18242:10"/>vnto vs, prepared for the King of Heauens triumphant entra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this world, to conquer Sinne, Death, and Hell for vs.</p>
               <p>She was (as <hi>S. John Damaſcene</hi> from an Apoſtolical tradition aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureth vs) conceaued of barren and aged Parents, that Grace might preuayle aboue Nature, &amp; Luſt haue no place in her holy Conception. <hi>S. Ioachim</hi> and <hi>S. Anne</hi> (ſayth this holy Father) were great Almes-giuers, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deuout perſons, both to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue at Gods hands, the bleſſing of ſuch a child; and that ſanctity likewiſe (as <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> writeth of <hi>S. John Baptist</hi>) might deſcend, as it were, hereditarily on her, in whome the Authour of ſanctity was to be contayned.</p>
               <p>An Angell is ſayd to haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tould her birth, by whome, the ruines cauſed in heauen by the fal
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18242:11"/>of Angells were to be repayred.</p>
               <p>Her Patents, hauing in pious vſes, giuen away, the greateſt part of their worldly ſubſtance, &amp; liuing as they did in a remote Prouince of Paleſtine, and that poore Village of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, as it were, the way to our heauenly Redeemers poore Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity, and humble life, lead af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward among vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladyes immaculate Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception.</hi> [Chap. 2.</head>
               <p>AS Almighty God had elected this ſacred Virgin, to the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gheſt office, and greateſt vnion with himſelfe, which a pure crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture could be aſſumed vnto: ſo did he no doubt, ſingularly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare her therunto, by conferring on her proportionable graces.</p>
               <p>For as from our Sauiours high
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18242:11"/>title, of being called the Son of God, <hi>S. Paul</hi> collecteth his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite excellency aboue the Angels, only called Gods Miniſters, and ſeruants: ſo may we in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner from this B. Virgins ſouerai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne title of being the mother of God, well gather her graces to haue been farre greater, then her diuine Father, Sonne, &amp; Spouſe had at any time before beſtowed vpon the greateſt of their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants.</p>
               <p>And, as ſhe concurred in an eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciall manner, to redeeme the world by communicating fleſh, and bloud, to the heauenly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer thereof, the high prices of our redemption: So did ſhe (no doubt) ſingularly partake the fruites therof, &amp; holieſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of being by him redeemed. That whereas other ſoules, in their firſt creation &amp; vnion with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18242:12"/>bodies, contracte the hatefull foulenes of originall ſinne; ſhe by her ſonnes ſweet bleſſing, was fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that fowle infection graciouſly preſerued: ſo as Nature, &amp; Grace began togeather in her, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily conſpired to make her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete, in naturall, and ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall perfection.</p>
               <p>As a bright ſtarre of the ſea, according to the myſterious ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of her name; a heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſplend our in her firſt riſing did wonderfully adorne her.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, out of which the flowing ſpring of all graces was to riſe; no filth of ſinne did euer defile her.</p>
               <p>As a liuely, and moſt louely tabernacle of the higheſt, ſhe was no ſooner rayſed, but the ſeauen-headded lampe of the Holy Ghoſt did flame in her: and as a myſterious Arke placed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18242:12"/>in the beautifull Temple of her body, her innocent ſoule, was with <hi>Cherubims</hi> wings, acts to wit of heauenly knowledge &amp; loue, graced and protected.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Syria's</hi> King had no power to caſt any of his deadly dartes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this euer holy, and diuinely guarded <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This louely ſpouſe of heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Aſſuerus,</hi> was from the rigou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous penalty of his lawes, made not for her, but for ordinary ſubiects, graciouſly exempted.</p>
               <p>The naturall, and immediate vnion which this ſacred Virgin was to haue afterwards with her diuine ſonne, preuay led far more with graces to enrich her, then her remote deriuation from <hi>Adam,</hi> ſinfully to infect her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eues</hi> oldnes, had no place in this new womans co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ception, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned to be the gracious hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18242:13"/>of the ſonne of God, in our heauenly regeneration, and in graces therfore to be likened vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.</p>
               <p>And ſurely, that particular en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, which Almighty God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to place betweene her and Satan, in the hearing of our firſt parents, importeth her, to haue byn dearely vnited to the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Author of that promiſe, &amp; neuer by any kinde of ſinne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thralled to him, ouer whome by her Sonne, ſhe ſo gloriouſly triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phed: Pious eares, and harts ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horring to heare ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that this ſacred mother of their heauenly Redeemer inherited ſinne (as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther children do) for her birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in this world, and became therby her enemies ſlaue, a child of wrath, hatefull to her diuine ſpouſe, and guilty for a tyme of eternall damnation. No certainly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18242:13"/>it could not be, but that he, who by aboundant graces preſerued her (as all Catholiques belieue) from venially offending him, by a like, and indeed far leſſe priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his loue, freed her alſo, from all mortall, and ſinfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our B. Ladyes Natiuity.</hi> [Chap. 3.</head>
               <p>THis dawning of our Eternall Day, (as the Church calleth the ſacred Virgin) being cleared in her firſt riſing, and brightly ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tled with that ſunnes beames, which to illuminate the whole world, roſe afterwards in her, <hi>S. Annes</hi> wombe, became as a quiet Oratory, for her to pray in, and render humble thankes to her diuine Lord, for his gracious fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours newly then conferred on
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18242:14"/>her, with ſuch an infuſed kind of knowledge, as <hi>S. Iohn Baptist</hi> had, when in his mothers wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be, at his Redeemers preſence, he ioyfully exulted.</p>
               <p>Her firſt graces actuall and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bituall, were ſuch (no doubt) as well became ſo diuine and libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall a Sonne, to beſtow, for her firſt welcome into the world, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſo deſeruing a Mother, as he foreſaw, ſhe would be vnto him.</p>
               <p>The Eternall Father likewiſe, began euen then, as his humble handmaid, graciouſly to reſpect her: and the ſubſiſting ſpirit of Loue and Bounty as his deſigned ſpouſe, by wonderfull graces, to indeare her vnto him.</p>
               <p>Angells, as their Lords future Mother, highly honoured this gracious Infant, and <hi>Gabriell</hi> a chiefe Prince amongſt them, was then appointed, and moſt gladly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18242:14"/>accepted to be a Guardian vnto her, by whoſe happy birth, and holy life, all mankind was to be graced and bleſſed.</p>
               <p>Her Infancy, was (as we may well call it) a holy Exerciſe of Charity towards God, brought into the earth with her, dutifull Loue to her Bleſſed parents, and glad Patience in ſuſtayning all infirmities common to children; reſembling then in her innocent, and holy demeanures, the like carriages of her diuine Sonne, in his childhood afterwards: ſo as ſhe had no way ward fancyes, or childiſh paſsions, ordinarily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the vſe of reaſon, and actuall graces, wanting in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther children: but Innocency gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced her, from her firſt entrance amongſt men, Purity conſecrated her to her diuine ſpouſe, Sanctity enriched her, Humility prepared
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18242:15"/>her to receaue from him frequent and wonderfull fauours, Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty did ſet out her rare bewtyes, &amp; made them more gracefull to ſuch as beheld her.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our B. Ladies Preſentation, and life in the Temple.</hi> [Chap. 4.</head>
               <p>THE mother of God, was in her tender yeares, to her own great comfort, and the merit of her holy Parents, planted (ſay th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>S. Iohn Damaſcene</hi>) as a fruitfull Oliue in the houſe of God, to become fatned there, &amp; to flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh with all graces.</p>
               <p>As another <hi>Hester,</hi> ſhe was tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated, into heauenly <hi>Aſſucrus</hi> Pallace, to be adorned there, ſweetned, and made ready for his future imbracements; where not <hi>Egeus</hi> the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> but Gabriel
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18242:15"/>a chiefe Angell with his glorious co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions, tenderly regarded her by the appointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of their Lord, and familarized themſelues with her.</p>
               <p>Her life there (as <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> deſcribeth it) was ſuch, as ſhe became therein, a mirrour to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of vertuous perfection. To her ſuperiours (ſayth he) ſhe was humbly obedient, courteous to her inferiours, and mildly ſweet to her equals; not eating oftner, or more at any tyme, then natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall neceſſity inforced her vnto; praying much, ſleeping litle, and neuer ſo, but that her hart was waking in a manner the while; often interrupting, with holy thoughts, the repoſe of her ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
               <p>Her bodily beauty, was like a flower, ſweetned with internall graces, and blowne forth to the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18242:16"/>fulnes of corporall perfection, neuer faded much in earth, and in heauen now gloriouſly repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
               <p>Her holy Parents hauing en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed themſelues, and yielded to the world, the bleſſing of ſuch a child, happily departed this life (as great Authours haue conie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured) during her aboad in the Temple, becauſe there is not in the Euangelicall Hiſtory any mention at all of them; as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynly there would haue byn, had they byn liuing at, and after our Sauiours Incarnation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our B. Ladyes Eſpouſalls to S. Ioſeph.</hi> [Chap. 5.</head>
               <p>THis ſacred pure Virgin liuing amongſt a carnall people, farre more reſpecting the bleſſing of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18242:16"/>children by marriage, then vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall integrity, and perfection, was about the 15. yeare of her age by the will of them, who were Rulers of the Temple, eſpouſed to a man of her owne Tribe, fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly choſen, firſt by God, and afterwards by them, as a husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d for her; ripe in yeares, chaſt in the profeſſion of his life, &amp; farre excelling (ſayth S. <hi>Bernard</hi>) as well in the future dignity of his office, as in heauenly ſanctity, that holy Patriarch, and beſt beloued ſonne of <hi>Iacob,</hi> whoſe Name alſo he myſteriouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed; a true heyre of <hi>Dauids</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, whoſe Sonne the Angell called him, and a man according to Gods owne hart, much more then he; worthy as a mortal man could be, to deuide the name of a Father with God himſelfe, &amp; to haue, as a good and faythfull
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18242:17"/>Steward ſuch heauenly treaſures, as were the Incarnate Word, and his gracious Mother, recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto him.</p>
               <p>Her being ſo eſpouſed, was (ſayth <hi>S. Hierome</hi>) for the legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of our Sauiours birth to the Iewes, and help of his educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion needfully required: and that alſo his being borne of a ſpotles Virgin, might be concealed from the diuell. Which reaſon allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by great <hi>Jgnatius,</hi> who liued to know her and our Redeemer himſelfe, ſeemeth to inferre, that neyther in the miraculous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of her child, or at any tyme after, infernall ſpirits dared to approach her, Angelically gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and like an Army ranged for a battayle, terrible vnto them.</p>
               <p>Holy <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was before mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage (as may be moſt probably gheſſed) made acquainted with
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18242:17"/>her virginall vow, &amp; being him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a Virgin purely and piouſly diſpoſed, moſt willingly yielded thereunto, and reſolued gladly to accompany her in the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance thereof.</p>
               <p>They liued to geather at her poore houſe in <hi>Nazareth S. Ioa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chims</hi> Sheepcote (as <hi>S. John Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcene</hi> calleth it) firſt graced with the B. Virgins happy birth, and afterwards more highly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifyed, by the diuine Words Incarnation, and life lead there from his returne out of Egypt, till after his Baptiſme: ſo that, as a ſacred monument of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and a ſure teſtimony of of our Sauiours pouerty, it was firſt by the Apoſtles themſelues, conuerted into a Chappell, and ſince, not only preſerued in the miſerable ruines of <hi>Palestine,</hi> but from place to place, likewiſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18242:18"/>for the greater veneration there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, by Angels tranſlated. Deuour people come from ſeueral Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes thronging vnto it; Princes haue with their votarie guifts &amp; Donaries enriched it; miracles haue wonderfully graced it; and where now it remayneth, it is as a moſt precious Iewell, cabbined in a curious Couering of white marble, and hath beſids a fayre Church built ouer it, wherin it ſtandeth as a moſt holy <hi>Sanctum Sanctoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> breathing ſanctity into the pious viſitours thereof, and delighting (I doubt not) heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Creatures to behod it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our B. Ladyes ſalutation by the Angell.</hi> [Chap. 6.</head>
               <p>THe ſacred Virgin, and her holy Spouſe, had not liued lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather, but the fulnes of tyme
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18242:18"/>was come, (as <hi>S. Paul</hi> calleth the happy inſtant of our Sauiours In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation) when the diuine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſent a chiefe Prince of their Court, as a Paranymph, to ſalute this pure Mayden from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and obtayne her conſent, to be diuinely fecundated by the holy Ghoſt, and haue the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Word Incarnate within her.</p>
               <p>Who, knowing the wonderful Excellency of her to whome he was ſent, ſaluted her with the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gheſt Titles, which could be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to an vnglorified Creature, ſaying, <hi>Hayle full of grace &amp;c.</hi> and he had further perchance dilated himſelfe in her prayſes, had ſhe not by her humble feare, ſweetly interrupted him.</p>
               <p>Calling her <hi>Mary,</hi> familiarly afterwards (which at firſt for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence he did not) he made her to know him, with whome, ſhe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18242:19"/>had often, and familiarly conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed before (as great Authours haue ſuppoſed, and is gathered from the Euangeliſts words) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming her to haue byn troubled not as his ſight, but at his ſpeach, and high Titles, therein giuen vnto her.</p>
               <p>Feare not (ſaid he) thou haſt found grace with God; ſuch a <hi>Grace</hi> indeed, as <hi>Heſter</hi> found in <hi>Aſſuerus</hi> eyes, and hart togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when as a louely ſpouſe, and Queene he meant to exalt her: Telling her further, that ſhe ſhold conceaue in her wombe, and bring forth a Sonne promiſed by God (as the reſt of his wordes do import:) foretould by his Prophets, <hi>Jſay</hi> eſpecially, whoſe very wordes he vſed vnto her; diuine in himſelfe, glorious like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, &amp; eternall in his kingdome.</p>
               <p>How (ſayd ſhe) ſhall this be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18242:19"/>done, becauſe I know not man? Which queſtion had byn idly made (as ſundry ancient &amp; great Fathers haue obſerued) had ſhe not byn debarred, by her virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall vow, from knowing her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</p>
               <p>When the Angell had cleared her difficulty, &amp; told her, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine &amp; pure ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of her ſonnes conception; with great humility and deuotion, ſhe threw herſelfe, as it were, into the opened armes of her omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t gracious Spouſe to be purely imbraced, and fecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated, with admiration and loue yielding herſelf vnto him: <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaid ſhee) <hi>the handmaide of our Lord, be it vnto me, as you haue ſaid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Happy Turtles voyce (ſayth <hi>S. Bernard</hi>) ſweetly vttered heere in earth, yet working wonders in heauen, by cauſing forthwith Gods eternall ſonne, to deſcend
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18242:20"/>from his Fathers boſome, into her ſacred wombe, and therin to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume humane Nature perſonally vpon him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the Eternall Word in her Bleſſed wombe.</hi> [Chap. 7.</head>
               <p>IN this miraculous Conception of God, and Man, our heauenly Redeemer, not the Eſſence, but the manner only of humane ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration was many wayes altered, and of the Virgins pure bloud a humane body was ſodainly, and perfectly framed, but not vnited with a gracious, and glorified ſoule, then created alſo, before they were by the diuine Word perſonally aſſumed, that ſhe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally concurring in her ſacred wombe to vnite them, might be the true mother of him that was perfect God, and perfect man, in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18242:20"/>one Perſon vnited.</p>
               <p>This Celeſtiall Babe, behoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding himſelf at that happy inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, by created graces, and a diuine greatnes, aboue all creatures infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely exalted, adored likewiſe by all the Quires of Angells, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day ned to redeeme mortalls, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all the deſigned children of glory, then preſented before him; he firſt, and moſt eſpecially beheld his holy Mother, in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture neereſt, in dignity chiefeſt, &amp; in loue deareſt vnto him, actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally then prepared in an humble ardour of heauenly loue to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, what graces he would giue her, whoſe guifts no doubt, equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his meaſureleſſe loue towards her, and aboundantly requited the harty welcome ſhe gaue him.</p>
               <p>And that her loue towards him naturally, as to her ſonne, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturally as to her God, might
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18242:21"/>then and afterwards become hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply increaſed; he is conceaued by great Authors, to haue at that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant infuſed into her ſoule, a clearer ſight of his perſonall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty and greatnes, then <hi>Moyſes,</hi> or any other Saint before her, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed, lying in her wombe as a louely Bride in his marriage bed ſweetly repoſed; as a tree of life newly planted in this heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe; as a fragrant fayre flowre out of her flouriſhing braunches graciouſly budded; as a pretious Margarite in a cleere mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearle ſafely incloſed; finally as an amourous louer ſweetly lulled in the Virgin-lappe of her, his chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly beloued, corporally growing in her nature, and liberally com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating his ſpirituall guifts, and graces vnto her.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:18242:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our B. Ladyes viſit of</hi> S. Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth. [Chap. 8.</head>
               <p>THis mayden-gracious-Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was no ſooner wakened out of her ſweet traunce of loue, &amp; diuine fecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dity, but Humility prepared, and feruent Charity incited her to vndertake a payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full iourney of 3. dayes trauell, ouer the craggy mountaynes of Iewry, to viſit her aged Coſen <hi>S. Elizabeth</hi> in <hi>Hebron,</hi> and to ſanctify <hi>S. John</hi> her ſonnes Precurſor, by the breath of her ſalutation; of which not the words, but effects are by the Euangeliſt declared, to haue byn heauenly light, and aboundant graces, diuinely infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into the child firſt, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther afterwards; which he with exultation, and ſhe with out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryes of ioy and loue, propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18242:22"/>vttered, conioyning in her bleſſings this ſacred mother, and her diuine ſon; as in nature then and loue ſhe beheld them graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly vnited: <hi>Bleſſed</hi> (ſayd ſhe) <hi>art thou amongst women, &amp; bleſſed is the fruite of thy wombe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bleſſed indeed in herſelfe, as hauing the height of all created bleſſings beſtowed vpon her; and bleſſed in her ſonne, the flowing fountayne of them. He, as the fruit of life growing in her wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be was bleſſed, and ſhe was bleſſed as the tree that bore him: &amp; ſurely ſuch a heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly fruit, as the Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat Sonne of God was, could not but haue a tree of rare goodnes to produce him, ſince the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of trees are by their fruites to be chiefly diſcerned. This di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine graine of corne falling from heauen into the earth according to his owne words in the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18242:22"/>had no doubt, a fat, and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile ſoyle to fall into; this preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous margarit of Heauen, had a cleere mother-pearle to breed it; this bright ſonne of Iuſtice final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had a fayre dawning to riſe in by his moſt reſplendent beames, before other Saints mantled and adorned. <hi>Whence is it</hi> (ſayd this Saint, admiring the B. Virgins Humility, and gratefull for her charity in comming to a perſon ſo much in dignity and graces in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour vnto her) <hi>that the mother of my Lord, is come vnto me?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Elizabeth</hi> was a great Saint, canonized and comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with her husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; yet being humble &amp; actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally illuminated to know the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnity and wonderfull graces of her Coſin, ſhe ſaw her owne ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles by the others huge flames in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>comparably exceeded; her ſmal
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18242:23"/>light by the others su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ecclipſed; and the mother of a Creature, by the bleſſed Parent of her Creatour and Redeemer himſelfe, incomparably excelled.</p>
               <p>Then gladly, &amp; thankefully ſhe acknowledged the holy effects in her child, and her ſelfe; of her ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutation, prayſing her beliefe yielded to the Angells ſpeaches, &amp; prophetically aſſuring her, that all ſhould be fulfilled, which he had tould her, concerning the greatnes of her ſonne, redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world by him, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his kingdome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladyes Canticle, and ſtay with her Coſin</hi> S. Elizabeth. [Chap. 9.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAint Elizabeth</hi> is ſayd to haue byn newly repleniſhed with the Holy Ghoſt, before ſhe ſpake to the mother of God; ſo were
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18242:23"/>
                  <hi>Zachary</hi> her holy husband, and <hi>Simeon,</hi> before they brake out into their propheticall Canticles. But before the B. Virgin entred into hers, no new inſpiration is mentioned; to let vs thereby know, that ſhe did no more ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, then a litle open the enriching Treaſures of diuine Loue, and knowledge, hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly by her before hidden, and euer concealed, but when in gratitude to the liberall Authour of them, ſhe was ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enforced to diſcouer them. And as her Coſin had magnifyed her, ſo did ſhe for them magnify her Lord: and as <hi>S. Iohn</hi> exulted in the wombe, ſo her ſpirit like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe exulted in God her Sauiour: an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble Propheteſſe afterwards (ſayth <hi>S. Baſil</hi>) of her owne future greatnes, and a deuout Preacher in the reſt of her high Canticle of her Creatour prayſes, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18242:24"/>eſpecially in ſending his ſonne graciouſly to redeeme vs. <hi>Behould</hi> (ſayth ſhe) <hi>from henceforth all Generations shall call me bleſsed, becauſe he that is mighty hath done great things to mee &amp;c.</hi> giuing vs to vnderſtand, that holy ſoules euen to the worlds end, ſhould admire Gods gracious goodnes towards her, and bleſſe not only him the Giuer, but her alſo the Receauer, of ſuch wonderfull bleſsings.</p>
               <p>Then ſweetly delighted to vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Gods mercifull loue to men, and dreadfull ſeuerity in tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling downe the proud Angells from their high ſeates for of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending him, ſhee concludeth her ſacred Canticle, with a fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent and gratefull acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that high Bleſſing of Bleſſings, which by her, he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to his people.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:18242:24"/>
               <p> She is ſayd, to haue ſtayed, about three monethes with her Coſin, that this holy family, might laſtingly enioy the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of her preſence, whoſe firſt approach had byn the cauſe of ſuch bleſſings vnto them; &amp; that the little Champion (as <hi>S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> calleth S. <hi>Iohn</hi>) might be the more fully annointed, and in the lappe and armes of this mayden, and gracious Mother of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Redeemer, haue new graces breathed into him. For by the Eccleſiaſticall order, of celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the feaſt of our Ladyes <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> the day after <hi>S. Johns</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaue, we are giuen to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that ſhe ſtayed with her Coſin, vntill the childes circumciſion.</p>
               <p>Holy <hi>Zachary</hi> likewiſe, no ſtranger in his owne houſe, nor vnworthy to haue theſe ſecrets of heauen imparted vnto him,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18242:25"/>may well be ſuppoſed, to haue heard, in his owne miraculous ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, the propheticall outcryes of his wife, and myſterious Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of his Coſin, po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dering them deuoutly in his hart, vntill with his tongue in the circumciſion of his child his ſpeach was reſtored, and himſelfe newly inſpired to add his owne Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ticle vnto them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our Sauiours Incarnation mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested to</hi> S. Ioſeph. [Chap. 10.</head>
               <p>AS the Mother of God, had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent graces, and fauours heaped from heauen continually vpon her; ſo had ſhe two excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vertues, Humility to wit, &amp; Taciturnity to hide them, which after her returne to <hi>Nazareth</hi> ſhe holily exerciſed. For in a ſhort tyme the happy grouth of her diuine Babe, appeared in her
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18242:25"/>wombe, and her ſacred breaſts, as pearly-bottels, tipped with ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byes, and filled from heauen, to nurſe God himſelfe, in humane nature, plainely diſcouered that to <hi>S. Ioſeph,</hi> her louing and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued Spouſe, which ſhe deſired not to haue hidden from him.</p>
               <p>Her knowne ſanctity, &amp; vowed purity of life, cauſed him not to ſuſpect on the one ſide, any adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous ſacriledge to haue byn committed by her, more &amp; more ſtil appearing gracious vnto him; yet ſeeing on the other ſide eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſignes of her being with child, ignorant (ſayth <hi>S. Hierome</hi>) of this high myſtery, and holily reſolued not to liue perplexedly with her, or to expoſe her to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy, and death ordayned by the Iewiſh law for adulterous wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, with a griefe (no doubt) proportionable to his great loue
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18242:26"/>towards her, and vnſpeakable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, which he tooke in her ſweet ſociety and preſence, he reſolued ſecretly, to leaue her: and ſhe the while, though dearely reſpecting him, reſolued not to ſatisfy him in his doubt, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealing, without a diuine war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, ſuch heauenly ſecrets reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued indeed by a heauenly meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger to be related vnto him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joſeph ſonne of Dauid</hi> (ſaid the Angell vnto him in his ſleepe) <hi>feare not to take Mary to thy wife, for that which is borne of her, is of the holy Ghost: she shall bring forth a Sonne, &amp; thou shalt call his name</hi> IESVS, <hi>for he shall ſaue his people from their ſinnes;</hi> ouerioying him (no doubt) by ſo happy a tidin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, &amp; comforting him far more, then his intended departure from ſo deare, and gracious a ſpouſe, had formerly afflicted him; for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18242:26"/>then he foreſawe, and with due thankfulnes acknowledged ſuch wonderfull fauours, and diuine bleſſings, as by being husband to ſuch a wife, and foſter-Father to ſuch a child, as was the Incarnate Sonne of God himſelfe, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer of the world, would be heaped vpon him; making many feruent reſolutions, with an aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full loue, &amp; glad diligence from thence-forth to ſerue them; and vttering them in a ioyfull and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing maner to his Bleſſed ſpouſe as humbly and thankfully acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pting them. Such calmes after ſtormes, Almighty God is wont, for their triall, and merit, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow on his ſeruants, &amp; children deareſt vnto him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:18242:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladies Expecting, &amp; lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging for the byrth of her Child.</hi> [Chap. 11.</head>
               <p>THe Indian Oyſters vſe to ſhut vp within their ſhells, Pearles which they haue bred, ſo faſt, as without violence they open not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, to yield vp ſuch trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: But it was not ſo, in this ſacred mother-pearle of Heauen, for as ſhe had in her Virginall wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be, for the worlds rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption, diuinely conceaued her ſonne; ſo was ſhe for this high end, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to produce him. Whome ſhe well knew to lye, as a rich treaſure mined within her body, which ſhould no ſooner be brought to light, but other holy perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, the ſheephards for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the 3. Kings, old <hi>Simeon, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> and many with them, would
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18242:27"/>togeather with her ſelfe, come to be enriched holily, and happly by it.</p>
               <p>Or like a burning cole buryed vnder hot embers, he was inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in her wombe, which bared and layd open, would ſparcle, &amp; ſend forth flames, with which the whole world was afterwards to be fired, lightened, and purged, according to his owne words in the Ghoſpell; <hi>J came to ſend fire into the world, and what will J, but that it should be kindled?</hi> Or like a rich Iewell he lay cabbined vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till his birth in her, with whoſe gracious luſtre, when it came to be expoſed, men and Angells, were to be exceedingly and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually delighted: or finally like ſome delicious holſome fruite, he lay shelled, and vntaſted, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he came by holy ſoules, to be reliſhed, and fed vpon.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:18242:28"/>
               <p> For her owne comfort alſo, this ſacred Mother deſired her ſonnes birth, with vnſpeakable longing, to ſee him, imbrace him, and performe all motherly du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties vnto him, which whilſt he lay in her pure wombe ſhe could not. All that ſhe could do there for him, was to adore him in his humility, yield the Encloſure of her body freely vnto him, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing him as he lay within it, eating chiefly to ſuſtayne him, eſteeming herſelf happy in bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him, and willing with her hart bloud, if ſhe could, to haue yielded nutriment vnto him. Who was not dull the whilſt, or careles in requiting her affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionate intertaynement; but as the ſunne is wont more &amp; more to mantle, &amp; cleare the Eaſterne part of heauen, before his riſing therein: ſo did this diuine foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18242:28"/>of heauenly charity, illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate, inflame, and adorne with his brighteſt beames, the ſoule of this ſacred Virgin, before his riſing from her, in our earthly Horizon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladies iourney to Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leem.</hi> [Chap. 12.</head>
               <p>CAEſars Edict haſtned odedient <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and his humble ſpouſe towards <hi>Bethleem,</hi> there to be enrolled, then a ruinous poore Village, and farre different from what it had byn, when great <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> as his fathers birth-place, with high wals, turrets, and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely pallaces guarded graced and enriched it, yet neuer dignifyed the ſame ſo much, as did theſe poore ſtrangers, by entring into it, and bringing with them <hi>Iſraels</hi> heauenly King, and great Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18242:29"/>to be borne there, as long before <hi>Micheas</hi> had propheſied; ſo as it ioyed in an vnſpeakable ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner this holy couple, to know that they were now arriued, at the deſigned place of their So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes and Sauiours natiuity.</p>
               <p>Weary of their foot-iourney friendles, &amp; as poore perſons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected at the Inne ſtored with richer gueſts, humbly &amp; patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly they betooke themſelues to a poore ſtable, or Caue there (as <hi>S. Hierome</hi> calleth it) to beaſts &amp; beggars equally expoſed; fitly choſen by the Sonne of God, notwithſtanding, as myſteriou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly represe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting the worlds eſtate darkened by inſidelity, &amp; with horrible ſinnes abominably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, at his entrance into it. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsing withall, the obſcurity, and vncleaneneſſe of ſoules, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he come by heauenly graces,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18242:29"/>to be borne within them, when of foule ſtables, they become cleane tabernacles for the diuine perſons to remayne in.</p>
               <p>The pouerty likewiſe of the place, and want of all things ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, aptly yield exemplar docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to holy ſoules, of contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for his ſake, pallaces, po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pes &amp; worldly commodities, which this heauenly King for our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and example, as in his birth, ſo throughout his whole life, vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly wanted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladies Child-birth.</hi> [Chap. 13.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAint Bonaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture,</hi> in a holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of this ſacred my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, conceaueth the B. Virgin being come to <hi>Bethleem,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the ſtable, to haue byn
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:18242:30"/>exceſsiuely repleniſhed with ioy that the long deſired houre of her Diuine Sonnes Natiuity ſo neerly approached: and whileſt proſtrate on her knees in prayer, ſhe delighted her ſoule with holy apprehenſions thereof, and lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to behold him, he miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly aſcended out of her vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opened pure wombe, into her bleſſed armes, ready to imbrace him.</p>
               <p>This high priuiledge (ſayth <hi>S. Bernard</hi>) of being a mother, yet remayning ſtill a Virgin, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing byn for her ſingularly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, whoſe child was God &amp; Man perſonally vnited, able in his power, &amp; willing in his loue to preſerue his Mother from all payne, impurity, and corruption: in ſo much as learned <hi>Suarez</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaueth the pure Neſt, in which this diuine Phenix and heaueuly
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18242:30"/>Bird of loue was hatched, and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened for his birth, to remayne entirely yet preſerued, as it was at his going out from it, that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells intellectually, and Saintes corporally alſo may tranſparent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in all eternity, and delighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully behold it.</p>
               <p>Inſteed of midwife, &amp; women to help her, Angels in their kings birth, gladly became his Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and her Attendants; ſo that a poore ſtable, by the happy birth of this diuine Babe therein, was ſodainly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted into an Empy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall heauen; a hard crib in which ſhe layd him, became this hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble Kings bed of State to repoſe in; poore cloutes in place of purple robes ſerued to inueſt him; and the papps of a poore maiden, fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from heauen then, as her wombe had byn before, ſerued to giue him ſucke, who fed the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18242:31"/>birds of the ayre at that inſtant, and attyred the flowers of the field in their fayre and various beauties; neuer greater, then in being ſo leſſened; neuer more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious then in being ſo obſcured; neuer more exalted, then in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo humbled; neuer more lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely, then in humane beauty aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed; neuer more powrefull, then in our infirmityes ſuſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Mercy moued him to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake the painefull taske of of our Redemption, Wiſedome guided him, Fortitude hartned him, and Charity moued him ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to imbrace whatſoeuer he ſaw needfull, or expedient to be done, or ſuffered therein for vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladyes intertayning the shepheards in Bethleem.</hi> [Chap. 14.</head>
               <p>THe Angells of heauen hauing ioyfully themſelues adored
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18242:31"/>their king, haſtned into the fields of <hi>Bethleem,</hi> to make the poore ſhephards, there watching their flockes, ſharers of ioyes with them. <hi>Feare not</hi> (ſaid the chiefeſt of them, appearing ſingly, and gloriouſly vnto them) <hi>for J come to, tell you a ioy which ſhall be to all people, becauſe a Sauiour is borne vnto you this day in Bethleem;</hi> and forthwith to ſecond theſe happy tydinges, the whole Hoſt of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, was ſeene trooping in the ayre, &amp; heard to ſing, in a myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious canticle, the fruites of our Sauiours comming in earth and in heauen: <hi>Glory in the highest to God, and peace to men &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And they were no ſooner mounted vp to heauen, but the ſhephards haſted to <hi>Bethlee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> where at the cribbe of Chriſt, they ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully vttered what the Angells had tould them. And our B. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18242:32"/>is ſaid myſteriouſly by the Euangeliſt to haue conſerued, and conferred all theſe things in her hart, aſwell to illuminate &amp; delight her ſoule, by a high, and amourous conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plation of them, as ſhe did all the paſſages of her ſonnes life afterwards: as alſo to be able, for the good of others, and inſtruction perchance of this Euangeliſt himſelfe, afterwards to relate them: who profeſſing (as he doth) in the beginning of his Ghoſpell, to haue collected the ſacred verities therof from ſuch, as had byn miniſters from the beginning, &amp; witneſſes of them; we may well thence inferre him to haue receaued from this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Virgins mouth, all ſuch particulers of our Sauiours In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, and infancy, as ſhe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone could teſtify vnto him, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing byn the chiefe, and happy
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18242:32"/>actour in them, called therefore by ſundry holy Fathers, <hi>the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>streſse of the Euangeliſts:</hi> and S. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill before his <hi>Theſaurus vpon S. Iohn,</hi> wondreth not, that like an Eagle he ſoared aboue his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, hauing had fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Lords Croſſe, this ſacred Arke and rich treaſury of heauenly knowledge reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended vnto him, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing liued with her diuine ſonne, as his moſt inward, and wiſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary 30. yeares togeather, was all that tyme ſitting, as it were, at a continuall ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quet, guſtfully feeding, &amp; delighting her ſoule, with the heauenly viandes of his myſterious ſpeaches, and actions, conſerued ſtill in her hart, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly conſidered.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:18242:33"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our Bleſſed Ladyes nurſing, and ſeruing her diuine Sonne.</hi> [Chap. 15.</head>
               <p>AS it is certayne that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour was complete in the graces, and glory of his ſoule, from the firſt inſtant of his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane conception, wanting only that experimentall knowledge, which was by degrees (as in vs) to be gayned by the vſe of his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: ſo are we to conceaue this diuine Babe, to haue byn wholy free from all waywardneſſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanenes, violency of paſsions, fancyes, and other childiſh im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, intuitiuely ſtill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houlding thoſe very obiects, which experime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tally he learned.</p>
               <p>And whereas other children, by frequent aſpects, come to know the faces of their Mothers,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:18242:33"/>and beginne a naturall loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, for continuall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours receaued; this diuine child did not only exteriouſly know his Mother, but interiourly alſo behold the humble thoughts &amp; enflamed affections of her ſoule towards him, her pure intentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and harty gladnes in doing mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly offices vnto him; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the wonderfull merit of them with heaped graces pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently requited them.</p>
               <p>For ſurely they apprehend mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly the diuineſſe of this child &amp; Theandricall ſublimity of his actions, who conceaue his hug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings, kiſſes, and other like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of filiall Ioue towards his B. Mother, to haue byn no more, then fruiteles and naked ſignes of childiſh affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as indeed they were continuall breathings of new graces into
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18242:34"/>her ſoule, euer humble and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to receaue them.</p>
               <p>Naturall &amp; ſupernaturall loue ſweetly conſpired (no doubt) to indeare them to ech other; He, as his naturall mother, and moſt excellent Creature, humanly and diuinly affected her; and ſhe, as her God, and Sonne reſpectful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adored, and delightefully ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him. Which harmony of mutuall loue, betweene them, neuer of her part ſinfully inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, happily ſtill increaſed; ſo as heauenly Creatures themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, were delighted to behould him recreated, and her enriched, by their mutuall affections.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladyes ſorrow in her ſonnes Circumciſion.</hi> [Chap. 16.</head>
               <p>THe ſonne of God was vpon the 8. day after his birth, in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18242:34"/>the pure partes of his body, paynefully circumciſed, that he might, as in the end, ſo in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his life ſhed painefully his bloud for vs. For we are not to conceaue, that he who was aboue all lawes, and the Author of them, ſuffered this wound, becauſe the Law commaunded him, but rather he made this law, that to fulfill the ſame, he might take an occaſion, to be ſo woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for vs.</p>
               <p>This bloudy ceremony, &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentall remedy of originall ſinne in Male children, (arguing therfore Chriſts wonderfull hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility in vndergoing it) was v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually performed in ech pariſh by ſome Leuite, appointed by his office to do it, and the houſe where the child was borne, was the ordinary place of perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it; ſo as the Bleſſed Virgin
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18242:35"/>may be conceaued, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſionatly to haue ſeene this firſt and paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wound, made in the tender body of her ſonne, as ſhe did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards behould his laſt woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges, agonyes, and torments, hauing byn indeed not caſually, but diuinely ordayned, to ſhare in ſufferings with him.</p>
               <p>Luſt, the beaſtly and ouer-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vice of men, was ſo hatefull to this heauenly Author of puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Sonne of an immaculate Virgin, as in the very entrance of his life, he ſeemed to proclayme war againſt it, by cauſing the pure partes of his owne body, to ſmart, and bleed, that from ſuch a fountayne of grace opened in himſelfe, his deuout children, from raging heates and impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes in theirs, might become af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards cooled, and cleanſed.</p>
               <p>Neither was this wound only
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18242:35"/>painefully made, but (as we read of <hi>Sichem</hi> and his people) the ſtiff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and ſmarting payne therof continued many dayes after: ſo as we may well call this wound, a paynfull taſt which our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Redeemer was pleaſed to take, of his bitter, and deadly chalice; and a ſharpe exerciſe of patience with-all, in his louing Mother, dreſſing this wound whilſt it continued, and often bathing it, with flowing teares of tender compaſſion, as ſhe did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, his deeper, and deadlier woundes, ſuffering ſtill in her ſoule his bodily torments.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladyes impoſing on her Sonne, the Name</hi> IESVS. [Chap. 17.</head>
               <p>WIth the ſacramentall ſigne of Circumciſion, children then
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18242:36"/>were wont to be enrolled in the number of Gods people; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this name IESVS, impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſaluation of mankind, he would not without ſhedding his bloud, whereby he was to redeeme vs, haue it impoſed.</p>
               <p>This Name, holy and high aboue all Names (as <hi>S. Paul</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs) was miſteriouſly impoſed vpon two <hi>Ioſua's,</hi> or <hi>Jeſus'es,</hi> ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of our Sauiour in reducing Gods people from their firſt and ſecond captiuity; but common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afterwards giuen to children, that the myſteriouſneſſe therof, might not become noted in him who was to performe the high office of ſauing mankind, chiefly by it imported.</p>
               <p>This name (IESVS) reuealed by the Angell to the B. Virgin firſt, and to <hi>S. Ioſeph</hi> afterwards, with the comfortable meaning
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:18242:36"/>thereof, was as Oyle powred out, to mollify the griefe of his wound felt in her hart, and ſtill to increaſe the gracious flame of her ardent loue towards him. It was like ſweet Muſicke in her eares, hony in her mouth, and a continuall iubily in her hart, to name it herſelfe, or heare others name it. Her ſons humane &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine greatnes hauing byn menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by the Angell vnto her, for this end chiefly that ſhe might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaue the myſteriouſnes of it.</p>
               <p>All vertues exerciſed by him in the worke of our Rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prion, his actions, his ſufferings, and fruites of them, in earth, and in heauen, were continually to her by that holy name (IESVS) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendiouſly, and ſweetely impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: ſo as wee may well affirme her, to haue begun that Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to this holy Name heere in
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:18242:37"/>Earth, which is now to the ſame in heauen alſo yielded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the Sages finding the Child with the B. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> [Chap. 18.</head>
               <p>THis humbled king of maieſty, and greatnes, was pleaſed to haue his poore birth graced by the comming of Gentill Princes, from the vtmoſt endes of the Earth, by the conductio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious and miraculous Star, in <hi>Bethleem</hi> to adore him, not deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in their high thoughts, by his pouerty, but appearing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as a king of heauenly maieſty and greatnes; purpoſely ſo hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and diſguiſed in humane nature, afterwards to redeeme them more louely and gracious, whilſt with adorations, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, and guifts they teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:18242:37"/>their faith in him.</p>
               <p>And as the Childs greatnes, ſo his B. Mothers Excellency was diſcouered, no doubt, diuinely vnto them. Wherefore to inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate their ioyes, by behoulding her alſo increaſed, the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt my ſteriouſly telleth vs, that, <hi>they found the child with Mary his Mother:</hi> viewing him as the bright Sunne of heauen newly appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in our earthly Horizon, and her as that cleere dawning which he had choſen to riſe in. His gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious beames adorned her, and ſhe with her naturall bewty had ſweetly attired him; ſo as her li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely and louely forme, was in his humane face delightfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled.</p>
               <p>Who in the ſilence of her ſonne, became (as we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue) his interpreter vnto them, and an humble relatour of ſuch
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:18242:38"/>myſterious verities, as in loue, &amp; dewty, they deſired to know of him, concerning the miraculous manner of his Natiuity &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, and what the Angell had tould her, of his owne future glory, with the eternall greatnes of his kingdom: how likewiſe he had byn promiſed to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarcks, <hi>Abraham, Jſaac, Jacob,</hi> &amp; <hi>Dauid</hi> her propheticall Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cely Father; foretold by the Prophets, and expected by faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full holy ſoules throughout all generations, according to the words of her diuine Canticle for merly vttered.</p>
               <p>She knew them to haue made a long iourney, and not likely to ſtay long with her Sonne, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially after the Angell had warned them for their returne. Humility therefore, moued by charity, euer in holy ſoules (and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:18242:38"/>moſt eminently in her, then and afterwards) conioyned, yielded to diſcloſe ſuch heauenly ſecrets of her diuine Sonne vnto them, as might confirme their faith, &amp; increaſe in abſence, their preſent loue towards him. So as we may well thinke, the day, and night which they ſpent in <hi>Bethleem,</hi> to haue byn a happy tyme, for their comfort, and inſtruction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our B. Ladyes Purification.</hi> [Chap. 19.</head>
               <p>THis facred Virgin albeit in the Conception and birth of her child rather purified then defiled, went notwithſtanding as other wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did, to be legally clenſed; carrying Chriſt into the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with her, there to be offered, and as other children ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſly redeemed. Who as the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:18242:39"/>Lord of the Iemple himſelfe, meant therby to make the glory of this ſecond houſe, greater then that of the firſt, as had byn fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tould by his Prophets, by being more highly graced and exalted by the corporall preſence of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in it: and that likewiſe ſuch holy perſons, as <hi>Saint Simeon,</hi> &amp; <hi>Saint Anne</hi> were, might happily enioy the promiſed and bleſſed ſight of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sincon</hi> is ſaid to haue entred the Temple (in ſpirit) diuinely, to wit, inſpired, and taught to know, amongſt ſo many chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as were there continually preſented, the bright Sunne of heauen (albeit then in humaue nature and pouerty wholy obſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured) ordayned to be after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a light to the Gentils, and the glory of his people, as he ſung in his Canticle, whilſt he
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:18242:39"/>enioyed the ſweet comfort of holding Chriſt in his armes for a moment, which the bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin and her Spouſe, for many whole yeares togeather, happily enioyed.</p>
               <p>And as if in ardent imbracings, and kiſſings of this diuine Babe, he deſired to haue gaſped out his holy ſoule into his ſacred mouth, breathing ſanctity into him, he cryed out to be diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and let forth of this world, that he might not liue perchance to ſee this beloued and gracious Lord of his hart, perſecuted in his Infancy, toyled in his life, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniated in his actions, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted in his doctrines, hared by thoſe whome he hartily loued, and finally to be, before his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers eyes butchered and diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</p>
               <p>So as he could not contayne
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18242:40"/>himſelfe amidſt his rauiſhing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments, from ſadly fortelling their ioynt griefes &amp; ſufferings; <hi>A ſword of ſorrow</hi> (ſayd he bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Mother of God, and her ſpouſe) <hi>shall paſſe through thy ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le;</hi> metaphorically ſo expreſſing that killing-wound, or rather thoſe many deadly woundes, which ſhold be made in her ſoule by behoulding, as ſhe did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, her ſonnes agonies, and torments: and inſinuating with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that noble kind of Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome which ſhe was to ſuffer, without other woundes, then ſuch as Loue made, by vniting her ſo neerly, and dearly to her ſonne, as to feele in her very ſoule, by a ſtrang kind of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, his corporall torments.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:18242:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our Bleſſed Ladyes flight with her Child into Egypt.</hi> [Chap. 20.</head>
               <p>THe Sages entrance into <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> to ſeeke a new King, <hi>troubled Herod,</hi> yet their priuate departure homewards another way, ſeemed to argue, that they had not found him; but when ſuch holy Propheticall perſons, (as <hi>S. Simeon,</hi> and <hi>S. Anne</hi> were knowne to haue byn) had ſo pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliquely proclaymed him, this bloudy Tyrant ſent out his mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous guardes, to kill all male Children of two yeares old and vnder, in, and about the Confines <hi>of Bethleem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the Angell had fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned S. <hi>Joſeph</hi> in the night, of this danger, Loue quickly awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened him and his B. ſpouſe, to prouide for the ſafty of the child,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:18242:41"/>by flying into Egypt, as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell had appointed them. Pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty eaſed their care of carrying much with them, &amp; the darkenes of the night, ſerued fitly to hide them from dangers approaching. The ſtrangenes of the Country which they were ſent vnto, did not trouble them; the length of the way did not terrify them; nor any other difficulty diſmay them occurring in their iourney, which they made through a ſandy vaſt Deſart ſo bleſſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſayth <hi>Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi>) by our Sauiours preſence as it became afterwards a holy, and ſolitary retyrement of innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Saintes, gladly leauing worldly noyſes, &amp; contentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, quietly there, and holily to ſerue him.</p>
               <p>Their manner of carrying the child ſo long &amp; paynefull a iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, may be ſuppoſed to haue
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:18242:41"/>byn no other, then beggars vſe, when truſſed at their boſome, or backes, from place to place, they carry their children. Idolls are ſayd to haue falne downe (as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon</hi> before the <hi>Arke</hi>) and oracles to haue ceaſed, when the incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Word and heauenly Author of Truth in that Countrey ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared.</p>
               <p>Their entertaynme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is by lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Suarez,</hi> conceaued to haue byn no other, then ſuch as beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars are wont to receaue amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt ſtrangers, vntill <hi>S. Joſeph</hi> by the exerciſe of his poore trade, was towards their reliefe, able to gayne ſomething. The place of their aboad is ſayd to haue byn neere <hi>Ramaſſes,</hi> a Citty built long before, by the Iſraelites hard la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, during their captiuity: and in that place is yet ſhewed a well, wherein the B. Virgin is ſayd
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:18242:42"/>haue waſhed her ſonnes cloathes, watring a valley of Balme-trees, onely growing in that part of the Country, as if from that ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied fountayne, the place had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued a ſingular vertue.</p>
               <p>The chiefe, and vnſpeakable Comforts of theſe holy Parents in their exile, may be thought to haue byn, the gracefull grouth of their diuine child, his wiſe ſpeaches after he could ſpeake, &amp; louing behauiours towards the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our B. Ladyes returne, with her Child out of Egypt.</hi> [Chap. 21.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>TAke the child</hi> (ſaid the Angell the ſecond tyme) <hi>and his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and returne into the land of Iſraell, for they are dead that ſought his life &amp;c.</hi> omitting not to giue the ſacred virgin her higheſt title, to wit of being Mother to ſuch
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:18242:42"/>a child, &amp; inſinuating withall by this manner of ſpeaking (as lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Suarez,</hi> with other great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors obſerueth) that this Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saint was to reſpect her, not only as his wife, but as the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his redeemer withall; who with a reuerentiall &amp; hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble kind of glad loue, yielded accordingly his ready ſeruices vnto her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Herod</hi> (as <hi>Baronius</hi> gathereth from <hi>Ioſephus,</hi> &amp; other Authors) dyed the 7. yeare after his mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Infants, at which tyme our Sauiour could not be carried backe agayne in the armes of his Parents, as he had byn brought thither, nor well vndergoe the trauell of ſo long a iourney, but that his charity was ſuch towards vs, as for our greater example, &amp; merit, he would not in his very infancy from labours, and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings be ſpared.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:18242:43"/>
               <p> His Parents returned with him to <hi>Nazareth</hi> a poore Village, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fines of <hi>Galile,</hi> where till his Baptiſme he liued ſo mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely, as he was reputed no other then <hi>S. Ioſephs</hi> naturall Sonne, ſucceeding him afterwards in his poore trade, and labouring to make a plow, who was able with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out labour to haue created many worlds at that inſtant; praying with the <hi>Nazarites,</hi> &amp; the whilſt, as their God, prayed vnto by them; gazing with his humane glorious ſoule on the diuine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and intuitiuely behoulding all created Obiects. So as he gayned no knowledg, but expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimentall from them, wherein with his yeares, he is by the holy Euangeliſt ſaid to haue increaſed, and ſeemed exteriouſly to mens eyes more and more gracious in his perſon, and behauiour, not
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:18242:43"/>by any new graces gayned in his bleſſed ſoule, euer conſummated in them, but in gracefull manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations, and expreſſions of ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity, and knowledge, ignorance being no defect of humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, needfull to be aſſumed by the ſonne of God, to make &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe for our ſinnes his intended ſatisfaction; but wholy indeed vnbeſeming him, who was to be the heauenly teacher of ſoules, and to deliuer the higheſt veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as a cleere behoulder of them more then all the Prophets be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and able to ſecure and warrant, after an eſpeciall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the infallible Authority of his ſpeaches vnto vs.</p>
               <p>With millio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of holier thoghts, then ordinary Soules can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, did his holy Parents con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually behould him, and draw from all his gracious behauiours
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:18242:44"/>and ſpeaches (his B. Mother eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially) as bees do gather ſweet hony from flowres, new motiues &amp; increaſe of loue towards him; and he the whilſt, was delighted in no earthly obiect more, then to ſee the wonderfull effects of graces in her ſoule, &amp; to behold modelled as it were, his owne vertues in her, as in <hi>Archimedes</hi> chriſtall Sphere, the vaſt Orbes of heauen, &amp; their ſeuerall motions were wonderfully expreſſed: her guifts and fauours continually from him receaued, being no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther indeed, then flowings of his fountayne, ſparcles of his flame, &amp; beames of his infinite bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Sinne for example, was repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnant in him, to the maieſty of his owne perſon, and ſhe by her neere vnion with him, was from the ſame, or any inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto totally preſerued. Acts of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:18242:44"/>vertue were Theandricall in him, and by the dooers perſon infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely dignified: and in her they were euer heroicall, and highly enobled by her wonderfull gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Finally, as in his bodily bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty he was like to her; ſo did ſhe in her ſoule reſemble more &amp; more his gracious perfections, that ſo in both ſexes humane nature might become graced and exalted, as it had byn before vilified by ſinne, and extremely debaſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our B. Ladyes finding her lost ſonne in the Temple.</hi> [Chap. 22.</head>
               <p>IT was an yearely cuſtome (as the Euangeliſt telleth vs) of Chriſt, and his Parents to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate as other deuout people did, their Eaſter in <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> the ſonne of God being pleaſed ſo to dignfy the Temple by his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:18242:45"/>therin, and grace thoſe le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall ſacrifices, the types of his Paſſion.</p>
               <p>The myſterious obſeruances of that Feaſt ended, <hi>S. Joſeph</hi> and his B. Spouſe returned home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, conceauing their diuine ſonne, then 12. yeares old, to haue gone with their kinsfolkes, and neighbours out of the citty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. Whome when at night they found not, with wearyed ſtepps, &amp; carefull thoughts, they returned backe againe, preſently to ſeeke him, and after much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and griefe, they found him the third day, amidſt the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours of the Temple, by his wiſe demaundes wonderfully aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing them.</p>
               <p>His Mother, when ſhe could come to ſpeake co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniently with him, with an humble expoſtula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ioy and loue, asked him:
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:18242:45"/>
                  <hi>Sonne why hast thou done ſo vnto vs?</hi> as wifely knowing he was not abſent, but by his owne will from them, <hi>thy Father and I, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing did ſeeke thee:</hi> naming her Husband firſt, to expreſſe her humble loue, &amp; reſpect towards him; and how her owne ſorrow, by his afflictions had byn increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, whilſt <hi>S. Ioſeph</hi> by ſilence ſhewed his reſpect to them both, his aufull Reuerence reſtrayning loue, from any ſuch boldenes, as the B. Virgin with a greater right, and neuer but with his leaue &amp; gracious allowance, vſed towards him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Know you not</hi> (anſwered our B. Sauiour) <hi>that I am to be in the things of my Father?</hi> Giuing them ſo to vnderſtand, that for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of his heauenly Father he had ſo ſtayed behind them: to teach perchance thoſe Doctours
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:18242:46"/>&amp; guides of his people by occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his wiſe queſtions, ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable verities, fit to be knowne and taught to others by them; &amp; that as the Iewes then, ſo now, wee might by ſuch a glimſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue his ſunny brightnes, &amp; thoſe enriching treaſures, of diuine wiſedome &amp; knowledge, which in his tendreſt yeares, were hoar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vp in him.</p>
               <p>We may alſo piouſly gheſſe him, priuatly and alone in thoſe 3. dayes of his abſence to haue vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited the holy places of his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſufferings, and with an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable ardour of loue, and prompt obedience, to haue made his primitiue offerings ſeuerally in them, and vented, in laſting prayers and proſtrations, the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent longings of his gracious ſoule, afterwards to vndergo them.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:18242:46"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>His Parents</hi> are ſaid <hi>to haue wondred at his words,</hi> and the B. Virgin, <hi>to haue conſerued and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred them in her hart;</hi> that ſo we might come truly to know, that ſhe did euer do ſo, letting none of her diuine Sonnes myſterious words and actions to paſſe, but that by conſeruing them in her freſh memory, &amp; pondering them deuoutly in her hart, ſheenriched and rayſed her illuminated ſoule continually by them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladyes life with her ſonne vntill his Baptiſme.</hi> [Chap. 23.</head>
               <p>THe Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſt concludeth our Sauiours whole life, from his being found in the Temple vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till his Baptiſme, in theſe words; <hi>He returned with his Parents, to</hi> Nazareth, <hi>and was obedient vnto them;</hi> to wit, by a voluntary ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:18242:47"/>of himſelf, and a louing readines to do what they would haue him: who priuy to his hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den maieſty and greatnes, with a louing boldenes, ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded him as their ſonne, that as God the whilſt, and their Redeemer, they humbly in their thoughts, and affections adored him.</p>
               <p>Wherfore we may well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaue the bleſſed order of that family, wherein three perſons only li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, one of them diuine, and the other two eminently holy, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing Humility, and Charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ech other; he in obeying, and they in commaunding him, for the glory of his Father, and future inſtruction of his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, ſubiected vnto them.</p>
               <p>He with filiall loue reſpected his gracious Mother as the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and inſtrumentall cauſe of his humane being, omitting at
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:18242:47"/>no tyme, the duty of a child to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her: and to <hi>S. Ioſeph</hi> his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted Father, he yielded a grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full behauiour for his many pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full labours, and fatherly offices towards him, with heaped graces (no doubt) and diuine fauours, from tyme to tyme, liberally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiting them.</p>
               <p>Their liuing with him alone, as his ſecretaries and ſeruants, for 30. yeares together (for <hi>S. Ioſeph</hi> may be thought, not to haue dyed long before our Sauiours Baptiſme) was as a long harueſt of heauenly merits plentifully by them both (according to their aboundant ſowing) happily rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. And as this ſunne of heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brightenes, by doctrine, and examplar actions, did ſhyne to others with whome he conuerſed after his Baptiſme, for 3. yeares together: ſo with the like, and a
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:18242:48"/>far greater clarity did he appeare louely, and imitably gracious in all his behauiours &amp; ſpeaches to theſe two only, knowing his greatnes, for 30. yeares together, &amp; conuerſing domeſtically with him, who were neither dull to conceaue, nor hard to belieue the myſterious verity of his ſpeaches vnto them. And if that be true which <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth, <hi>that with the good, a man shall be good;</hi> how good then were theſe two who liued with goodnes it ſelfe, and had their ſoules euer opened, and prepared to receaue full ſtreames flowing from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne therof, continually into them?</p>
               <p>And if our Sauiour proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the eyes of his diſciples hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in hauing ſeene him, whome ſo many Kings &amp; Prophets had deſired to ſee, and could not; and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:18242:48"/>their eares likewiſe bleſſed in hearing his ſpeaches: how happy, and bleſſed may we conceaue his holy Parents to haue byn, who with eyes and eares of ſoule and body together, more laſtingly, clearely, and deuoutly beheld their diuine Sonne, pondering his myſterious ſpeaches, and in their hartes (as it is ſayd of the B. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin twice by the Euangeliſt) deeply, and delightfully conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the B. Virgins charitable ſorrow, for</hi> S. Ioſephs <hi>death.</hi> [Chap. 24.</head>
               <p>WHen this Bleſſed man dyed, cannot out of the Ghoſpell be any wayes gathered: Only it may moſt probably be gheſſed, that our Sauiour ſent him to a happy reſt, before he began his owne preaching &amp; labours. The
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:18242:49"/>place of his death is likeſt to haue byn in <hi>Nazareth,</hi> where he liued, and the circumſtances therof are vnknown further, then that as he was a <hi>iust man,</hi> aduanced to a dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity more then Patriarchicall, in being ſpouſe to the Mother of God, and Foſter-father to the incarnate Word himſelfe, ſo was his end no doubt bleſſed, and his merits ſuitable vnto it.</p>
               <p>And whereas we read of many Saintes, ſo diuinely fauoured in their ſickneſſe and death, as they had their good Angells viſibly &amp; comfortably attending them; this Bleſſed man enioyed a far greater priuiledge, when in his ſickneſſe and death, the ſonne of God himſelfe, and his gracious mother, with a moſt charitable dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce were ready to performe all ſeruiceable offices vnto him.</p>
               <p>The diſeaſe of which he dyed,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:18242:49"/>ſeemeth to haue byn old age, and the vſuall infirmities thereof, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed perchance in him, by the hard labours of his life, as Pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granuts vſe to breake and fall to the ground, by the ouer-filling grouth of their ſweet kernells, to riſe againe in a new ſpring after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
               <p>And whereas holy Men are ſaid to dye in our Lord; Bleſſed <hi>S. Ioſeph,</hi> may be ſaid to haue dyed in him after a higher man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; to wit, repoſed in the armes &amp; imbacements (as we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue) of his heauenly Redeemer, his immaculate louing Spouſe not fayling the whilſt to cloſe his dying eyes, to kiſſe his cold cheekes &amp; with flowing ſtreames of teares, to take her leaue of him by whome liuing ſhe, &amp; her diuine Sonne had byn ſo purely beloued and faithfully ſerued.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:18242:50"/>
               <p> His gracious ſoule was no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner breathed out, but Angells there preſent ioyfully carryed it to the holy troopes of Patriarks, Prophets, and Saintes diſceaſed before him, as their heauenly Redeemers Foſter-father, to be honoured, imbraced, and ioyfully welcommed by them, whilſt his Spouſe &amp; her diuine So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, cauſed his pure body, to be decently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred, &amp; put into the earth; where perchance, it was from corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption graciouſly preſerued, to be gloriouſly repayred in our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours Reſurrection, with other ſaintes bodies then miraculouſly rayſed; ſince no Saint deſerued more then he, to accompany his God, and Sonne, at his firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into his heauenly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:18242:50"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the Bleſsed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin, being in</hi> Cana <hi>with her ſonne at a wedding.</hi> [Chap. 25.</head>
               <p>AFter <hi>S. Joſeph</hi> his death, the B. Virgin liued alone with her diuine ſonne, flowing in heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delights, then without a part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, receaued continually from him, vntill his going to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized by <hi>S. John</hi> in the Riuer of <hi>Jordan:</hi> whence after his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, faſting in the deſert, and calling of many diſciples to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, he returned into <hi>Galilee,</hi> and was with his B. Mother at <hi>Cana</hi> inuited to a wedding, my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriouſly graced, &amp; ſhewed not to be ſinfull (as ſome ancient He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques affirmed) by the ſacred preſence of two ſuch gueſts, who pleaſed to be preſent at the ſame.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:18242:51"/>
               <p> Whoſe wedding this was, is not known, but that the Brides were poore, may be well gathered, from their want of wine before the Dinner was ended: which want of theirs, being knowne by the mother of compaſſion, ſhe came to her ſonne well knowing his diuine power to effect, &amp; her owne graciouſnes to obtayne what ſhe meant to aske of him, ſaying, <hi>they haue no wine,</hi> briefly intimating ſo their wantes, and her owne charitable deſires of relieuing them, to him, who without words did (ſhe doubted not) know them before hand, &amp; would in his bounty there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently redreſſe them.</p>
               <p>His reply <hi>(woman what is that to thee, and me?)</hi> was not harſh (as <hi>Caluin</hi> wickedly affirmed) but myſterious; to let vs therby know, that not her will (albeit
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:18242:51"/>euer holy and pleaſing vnto him) but the decree of his eternall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did in doing miracles chiefly direct him. And by telling her, <hi>(that his houre was not yet come)</hi> yet doing withall what ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated him, he gaue vs ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to vnderſtand, that her requeſt made him to exerciſe, ſooner the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> otherwiſe he would haue done, his miraculous power, in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that charity which ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated ſo of him; and by going afterwards to the wayters, and bidding them do whatſoeuer her Sonne commaunded them, ſhe wiſely and charitably prepared them (as Cardinall <hi>Tolet</hi> well noteth) not to hinder by their vnwillingnes, what ſhe knew he intended, as hauing byn diuinely inſpired to aske that miracle of him, and taught to know withall his manner of performing it, by
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:18242:52"/>cauſing, to wit, water to be drawn by the wayters, afterward into wine miraculouſly conuerted.</p>
               <p>And the fruites of this firſt miracle ſo obtayned by her, are ſaid to haue byn, the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her ſonnes glory, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of his diſciples.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladies going to dwell at</hi> Capharnaum, <hi>with her Son.</hi> [Chap. 26.</head>
               <p>OVr B. Sauiour, intending whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he began to preach, to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre his dwelling from <hi>Nazareth</hi> to <hi>Capharnaum,</hi> is ſayd to haue taken his B. Mother with him, that mutually they might enioy ech others company, and withall that ſuch perſons as were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted vnto him, might haue her a liuely mirrour of vertuous and exemplar perfection, conuerſant with them.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:18242:52"/>
               <p> So that this heauenly Sun of Iuſtice, ſhining heere on earth, had two <hi>Maries,</hi> bright ſtarres indeed of the Sea (as their names importe) illuſtrated by him in their ſeuerall graces, and wayting louingly on him; the one euer a cleere mirrour of vnſpotted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the other a liuely patterne at length of harty Contrition: Graces were in the one, as a bright ſun-ſhine, neuer ſinnefully clow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; and in the other as a radiant sky from ſtorms newly cleared. The one was as a full fountayne of liuing waters neuer defiled; &amp; the other as a deepe well, freſhly clenſed, and filled. The one neuer wanted a rich patrimony of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly graces, ſtill by her won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully increaſed; &amp; the other had hers, once waſted, graciouſly agayne, and with a great increaſe happily reſtored: and both were
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:18242:53"/>to him in their ſweet ſocietyes eſpecially delighfull, contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his ſpeaches, and noting his actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, to enrich their ſoules ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily by them; ſhe eſpecially, who from his childhood had byn ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to do ſo; conſidering his miraculous curing of diſeaſed and miſerable perſons not onely as acts of gracious loue and mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy towards them, on whom they were wrought: but as miſterious repreſentations likewiſe, of the like ſpirituall wonders, which then, &amp; after he meant to worke in ſoules, by his heauenly graces.</p>
               <p>Honours likewiſe done, and thankes yielded vnto him, for benefits receaued, delighted her humble ſoule; not only becauſe they were deſeruedly giuen vnto him, but for that wiſely likewiſe ſhe knew how liberally he meant afterwards to requite the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. As co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:18242:53"/>his diſgraces much grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued her, not only as iniuries done vnto him, who no wayes deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued them; but as they were great ſinnes in ſuch as did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit them, &amp; meanes to increaſe their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall damnation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the woman bleſsing the wombe &amp; paps of the B. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin.</hi> [Chap. 27.</head>
               <p>IT cannot be doubted, but that ſuch as belieued Chriſt to be the ſonne of God, and their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Redeemer, highly alſo reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected his gracious mother, loue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in her perſon, and exemplarly holy in her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation amongſt them; inſo much as a woman, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhed with the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſweetnes of our Sauiours words, and diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely rayſed in her thoughts to apprehend the bleſſednes of his Mother, vttered firſt that myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious outcry, <hi>Bleſſed is the wombe
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:18242:54"/>that bore thee &amp; the paps which thou didſt ſucke;</hi> and ſince enlarged by the Church in that ſweet verſicle ſung by her: <hi>Bleſſed are the bowells of Mary the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin, which carryed the ſonne of the eternall Father; and Bleſſed be the pappes which nurſed Chriſt our Lord:</hi> fulfilling therein her owne humble propheſy, <hi>that all generations should bleſſe her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither did our B. Sauiour in his reply to the woman, <hi>Yea but bleſſed are they that hear the word of God and keep it,</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradict the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of his mother; but (ſaith ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable <hi>Bede</hi>) was couertly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to intimate a more high and imitable commendation of his Mother, for that ſhe had not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly corporally, but ſpiritually alſo conceaued him; wherby ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued not the womans bleſſing alone, but to haue his own pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes added vnto it.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:18242:54"/>
               <p> For as learned Interpreters note vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this miſterious paſſage of the Ghoſpell, this ſacred Virgin may after two manners be conceaued to haue byn the Mother of God; firſt barely, to wit, according to his corporall Conception and Natiuity, and ſo it was poſſible, for her to haue byn his mother, without any graces at all therby obtayned: and ſecondly as ſhe was ſingularly choſen, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with wonderfull graces, to that high office, of giuing a new nature, life, and being to her om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent Creatour, for the glory of himſelfe, and redemption of mortall Creatures; wherby ſhe was rayſed to the higheſt digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and greateſt vnion with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, which a pure Creature could be aſſume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vnto: Gods vſuall manner hauing euer byn as he rayſed his ſeruants to high dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:18242:55"/>to beſtow on them ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble graces. And it were a moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable wickednes to conceaue, that he dealt otherwiſe with his owne moſt ſacred, and beloued Mother, who as in Nature was neereſt, ſo in Loue was no doubt, deareſt vnto him.</p>
               <p>It is true, indeed, that as his creature, ſhe was tyed in duty to do all motherly offices and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices vnto him, without any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bligation on his part, in iuſtice to requite them: But ſuppoſing the gracious, and free tye of his owne liberall promiſes, not to let ſo much as a cuppe of cold water, giuen for his ſake, paſſe vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, togeather with the duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full loue and piety of children towards Parents, commaunded by himſelfe and accordingly, no doubt, obſerued, may we not reaſonably conceaue, &amp; piouſly
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:18242:55"/>aſſure our ſelues, that he was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the piety of a louing child nor bounty of a gracious Lord, wanting vnto her, who not only gaue him the integrity of human nature, but ſpent her whole life afterwards, in motherly offices, and ſeruices towards him, for which other children can make to their parents no equall requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall.</p>
               <p>And ſuppoſing the sonne of God was able to rayſe his moſt deſeruing Mother to what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ſanctity, and heauenly nobility he would, for the good of her, and glory of himſelfe, to whome ſhe ſo neerely appertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; why ſhould any Chriſtian, againſt the knowne goodnes of ſuch a Lord, and Sonne, doubt him actually to haue done ſo?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:18242:56"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our B. Ladyes expecting her Son, at the doore of a houſe in</hi> Caphar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naum. <hi>Math. 12.</hi> [Chap. 28.</head>
               <p>OVr Sauiour teaching &amp; doing miracles within a houſe at <hi>Capharnaum,</hi> being tould that his Mother, &amp; Brethren (for ſo his Coſins are called in Scripture) ſtayed at the doore to ſpeak with him; eyther not willing to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted in his holy diſcourſes, or glad rather of the occaſion, to teach his Auditory a profitable leſſon, to wit, how they alſo might ſpiritually become his Mother and Brethren, he exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his hands towards his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, <hi>asking, who is my mother, and who are my Brethren?</hi> And then anſwering himſelfe ſayd, with an earneſt aſſeueration to the future comfort, and inſtruction of his
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:18242:56"/>ſeruants, <hi>He that heareth my words and keepeth them, he is my brother, my ſister, and my mother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Inſinuating ſo, in the very or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his ſpeach, by naming a Mother laſt, the eſpeciall neerenes of a mother to a child, and ſo conſequently her dearenes to him, who not only in her body corporally, but ſpiritually alſo in her ſoule, had conceaued, nurſed, and brought him vp, to a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull ripenes of heauenly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; and was like to become in others a fruitefull Parent, and Nurſe afterwards of him, being by her examplar life, as a ſweet odour to draw others into the bedchamber of her ſonne (ſayth <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi>) to be eſpouſed, &amp; fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundated alſo diuinely by him.</p>
               <p>Her motherly power ſayth an other deuout Author, hath byn the protection and helping of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerables
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:18242:57"/>ſoules to grace and glory; her greatnes their gayne, her treaſures their enrichings, by being able, and euer ready, to obtayne fauours &amp; bleſſings for her ſounes children, by himſelf therefore vpon his Croſſe recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended vnto her.</p>
               <p>So that they belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g not to him or her (as children or ſeruants) who haue vilified her in their thoughtes, and debaſed her in ſpeaches, ſo farre as to teach, that her diuine Sonne, did in thoſe former words blame her for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupting him vnſeaſonably in his doctrine, and plainely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce her for his mother: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Euangeliſt only affirmeth her, to haue ſtayed at the dore expecting him. And it proceeded out of the reſpect rather of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers towards her, that he was could of her being there, then
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:18242:57"/>that of her ſelfe, ſhe ſought to ſpeake importunely vnto him.</p>
               <p>And ſhould ſhe for iuſt cauſes or not, haue done ſo, had it not byn againſt the very duty of a child towards a Parent (as ſhe was knowne to be vnto him,) common diſcretion alſo, &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality it ſelfe, for ſo ſmall a fault ſcandalouſly and publiquely to renounce her?</p>
               <p>O monſters of men and vipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous brood of him whoſe head ſhe cruſhed happily for vs, that dared (as ſome moderne hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques haue done) to vtter ſuch horrid, and groundeſſe blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes agaynſt her! Whome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the humble prophecy of her ſelfe, <hi>all generations,</hi> of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſoules, <hi>were to call,</hi> and account eternally <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> as well for thoſe great things, which Almighty God, did vnto herſelfe, as for
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:18242:58"/>thoſe many &amp; vnſpeakable bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings likewiſe which by her he beſtowed vpon vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our Bleſſed Ladies ſuffering with her ſonne.</hi> [Chap. 29.</head>
               <p>AS <hi>Eue</hi> (ſayth <hi>S. Auſtine</hi>) was made to helpe <hi>Adam,</hi> in mans naturall propagation; ſo was the B. Virgin ordayned, to help the ſonne of God in our ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall regeneration. Thoſe two were our old, and theſe two our new Parents: they, threw vs mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably downe, from the happy eſtate of innocency to ſinne; and theſe, to more then loſt graces happily rayſed vs. Humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was in them by ſinne vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and debaſed, in both ſexes; but contrarily by theſe, won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully dignified and exalted.</p>
               <p>The ſonne of God by his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:18242:58"/>ſoly redeemed vs, as <hi>Adam</hi> by his fault only condemned vs: yet withall, as <hi>Eue</hi> our old Mother by eating the forbidden fruit, &amp; cauſing her husband to do the ſame, occaſioned our ruine; ſo <hi>Mary</hi> our new Mother, by behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the fruit of her wombe faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the tree of the Croſſe, happily co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>curred to our rayſing; &amp; by ſuſtayning deadly ſorrow, with her diuine Sonne in his death, recompenced, in a ſort, the others fault, and ſatisfyed for <hi>Eues</hi> ſinfull ſenſualities, by her innocent ſufferings.</p>
               <p>For albeit ſhe ſhed nor her bloud, nor had the faire Temple of her body, by woundes (as her Sonne was) lamentably defaced; yet ſuffered ſhe a higher kind of Martyrdome, when loue ſo vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her vnto him, as his agonyes became hers, by a tender com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:18242:59"/>his griefes her dolours, his torments her tortures, his corporall woundings paynefull rendings of her very ſoule, and ſharpe thruſts of that piercing ſword of ſorrow, which good old <hi>Simeon</hi> had foretold her. So that ſhe could not haue liued to the end of them, had ſhe not byn ſupernaturally aſsiſted, to offer iointly with him to his Eternall Father, that redemptory Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iacobus Acosta</hi> in his booke <hi>de Christo reuelato,</hi> affirmeth the Royall Pſalmiſt to haue ſung the 19. Pſalme in the perſon of this B. Virgin, ſtanding vnder the Croſſe of her ſonne: <hi>Let our Lord heare thee in this day of thy tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; the name of</hi> Iacobs <hi>God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect thee. Let him ſend help vnto thee, from his ſanctuary; and from</hi> Syon <hi>defend thee. Let him he mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:18242:59"/>of thy whole ſacrifice; and thy holocaust become a fat one. Let him giue vnto thee according to thyne owne hart; and confirme all thy coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell. We will reioyce in thy ſaluation</hi> &amp;c. <hi>So that when in the Antiphone of Aduent</hi> (ſayth this deuout Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor) <hi>the Church ordayneth me in her office to ſay before that Pſalme,</hi> Maria dixit, <hi>I ſeeme to be therby, warned, as in the perſon of this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Mother, and with a ſad memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of her ſufferings, vnder her ſonnes Croſſe, deuoutly to pronounce it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladyes last leaue taken of her Sonne in</hi> Bethania <hi>the euening before his Paſſion.</hi> [Chap. 30.</head>
               <p>WE find not any where expreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed in the Ghoſpell, that the Mother of God, was with her ſonne the day before his death in <hi>Bethania,</hi> as we read of <hi>S. Mary
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:18242:60"/>Magdalens</hi> being there, and his Apoſtles with him: yet is there an inſinuation, that other gueſts likewiſe were there preſent, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whome we cannot reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably conceaue his B. Mother, deareſt aboue all vnto him, to haue byn excluded; or that he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted his affectionate &amp; laſt reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect vnto her, appointed to ſhare the next day in deadly agonies with him.</p>
               <p>But piouſly rather &amp; prudently we may conceaue him to haue armed her for his farewell, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt griefes then approaching, by manifeſting, firſt his Fathers holy will vnto her, and the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious cauſes of her ſufferinges; ſecondly by telling her the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py fruites which were in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and in earth to redound af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards of them; and thirdly how ſhe was with himſelfe to be
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:18242:60"/>glorifyed Eternally for them: Counſelling, and enabling her by heauenly graces withall, to carry her ſelfe, (as ſhe did) man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in them, when without out-cryes, ſoundings, or other paſsionate, and vnſeemely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsions of her griefes, ſhe ſtood by his Croſſe (as the Euangeliſt telleth vs) letting downe ſilently into her ſoule, the whole bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes of his Chalice, and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as it were her breſt, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the ſaddeſt, and deadlieſt ſtroakes which affliction could lay vpon it.</p>
               <p>His laſt words to her, were (as we may conceaue) vttered with teares, and ſadde expreſſions of loue and compaſſion towards her for thoſe innocent ſufferinges which were to be by his torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſoon afterwards occaſioned. And ſhe for her laſt farewell to him,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:18242:61"/>may be thought to haue vttered ſome ſuch words as theſe, with motherly &amp; affectionate imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinges: Go my gracious ſonne, and heauenly Redeemer to pay on thy paynefull Croſſe, the high price of our Eternall Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wiſely no doubt, and iuſtly by thy diuine Father exacted. Let this goodly Temple of thy ſacred body, framed of mine, and miraculouſly raiſed, with bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy woundes in ſight alſo of me thy louing Mother, &amp; obedient Creature, be (as thy cruell Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries ſhall pleaſe) lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and painefully defaced; for now I can do no more motherly offices and ſeruices for thee: I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer heere my ſelfe willingly, to ſuffer all extremities with thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:18242:61"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our B. Ladies ſeuerall griefes in her Sonnes paſsion.</hi> [Chap. 31.</head>
               <p>AS our B. Lady is expreſly ſaid to haue ſtood neere to her ſonnes Croſſe in the tyme of his paſſion: ſo is it moſt probable, that ſhe ſadly beheld him in all his other publique torments, and diſgraces, fearing not as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Iewes did to be defiled, by entring the <hi>Pretorian,</hi> &amp; Courtes within it, ſanctified by her ſonns preſence, and ſacred ſtreames painefully in them effuſed.</p>
               <p>So that the accuſations vrged by the Iewes to <hi>Pilate,</hi> and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with outcryes againſt him, were as dolefull &amp; deadly ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of her ſorrow. Diſgracefull cueltyes done by <hi>Herod</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards &amp; his ſoldiars againſt him were as vnſheathings of that ſharp
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:18242:62"/>ſword which afterwards pierced her hart. The loud blowes and bloudy ſtripes lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tably tearing all partes of his body, were as wide rendings of her ſoule, and deadly piercinges of ſorrow.</p>
               <p>His thorny Crowne did ſharpen the ſwordes point, and make it enter more deeply; and finally <hi>Pilats</hi> ſentence, was as the ſtroke of a deadly thunderbolt vnto her.</p>
               <p>Her iourney after her Sonne to Mount Caluary, was to them both, mutually grieued for ech other, a dolefull proceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where the gaul giuen him, did increaſe the bitternes of her ſorrowes; &amp; when ſhe ſaw his cloathes pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked off, and raggs of fleſh clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vnto them, the ſmart of his woundes became in her ſoule freſhly renewed; &amp; when ſhe ſaw him mercileſly throwne downe
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:18242:62"/>on the hard bed of his Croſſe, ſhe alſo was caſt downe into the loweſt depth of griefe with him; &amp; had euen her hart pierced with thoſe very nayles, which entred into him.</p>
               <p>Thoſe bloudy ſtreames which ſhe ſaw running from him to the ground, and there trodden vnder the Hangmens feet, did make the woundes of her ſoule bleed fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhly; ſo, as ſhe became cooled at that ſad ſpectacle, &amp; had inſtantly died (as perſons do, wounded in the hart) had ſhe not byn, to ſee her ſonnes ſacrifice fully ended, ſupernaturally preſerued.</p>
               <p>The Iewes were myſteriouſly forbidden by their law, to boyle the Kid in his Dams milke: yet heere they did more, when they cauſed the child to be crucified in the ſight, and hart of his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by loue, and compaſſion
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:18242:63"/>ſo neerly, and dearly (as ſhe was) vnited vnto him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of Christs ſpeach to his mother and diſciple, vpon the Croſſe.</hi> [Chap. 32.</head>
               <p>THis God of loue and mercy (as we may well call him) ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bent like a bow on his Croſſe, was no ſooner lifted from the ground, but he began to dart vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, towards the boſome of his Father, fiery and flaming ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of loue to him, &amp; men to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather: firſt charitably excuſing and praying for his enemies, who at the ſame inſtant blaſphemed, and derided him, <hi>Father forgiue them for they know not what they do.</hi> Secondly, of tender and deare compaſſion towards his B. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, dying togeather with him, <hi>woman</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>behould thy ſonne,</hi>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:18242:63"/>meaning <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſtanding by her; and then to him, <hi>Behould thy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He called her, <hi>woman,</hi> leaſt by naming her <hi>Mother,</hi> he ſhould haue moued the Iewes to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages againſt her, and myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly inſinuating her withall, to be that woman which was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned to cruſh the Serpents head long before, and vtterly to vanquiſh him. And he ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended her for a Mother to <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> as we alſo had a ſhare (albeit after him) in this myſterious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption; ſo that we haue reaſon to glory, &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke him for a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble adoption: wherby he vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to make vs, as by his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo by his Mother likewiſe, bretheren vnto him; that, to the dewty which all owe her, for being Mother vnto himſelfe, we might add filiall piety alſo, and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:18242:64"/>ſeruiceable loue, to her who was euen as a Mother from his Croſſe recomme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, to obtayne graces of her ſonne, and Motherly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, temporall and eternall for vs.</p>
               <p>Who indeed, if we conſider the ſad tyme, and circumſtances of our adoption, whilſt he with torments, and ſhe with griefes were togeather languiſhing, we may be rightly called, as <hi>Beniamin</hi> was by his dying Mother, <hi>Benoni, Sonnes of ſorrow;</hi> yet children of her loue withall, if we conſider, well that ardent Charity, with which her diuine ſonne bequea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed vs for children vnto her; &amp; that humble Loue, with which ſhe accepted vs from him, actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dying then with herſelfe, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly to redeeme vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:18242:64"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our B. Ladies particular ſorrow in the death, and buriall of her Sonne.</hi> [Chap. 33.</head>
               <p>OVr B. Sauiour hauing hung ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently on his Croſſe for almoſt three houres togeather, to taſt more quietly, and feelingly the extremity of his torments (much increaſed throgh the coldnes of the ayre, darkened about him) awakened himſelfe, and his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Mother buryed as it were in a traunce of deadly ſorrowes, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with him, by a loud com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint made to his eternall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of being forſaken, and in the ſenſitiue part of his humane nature, left comfortles by him, <hi>O my God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> and rouſed himſelfe vp withall to dye as it became him, breathing out his euer-bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:18242:65"/>ſoule <hi>into the hands of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his body was dead &amp; cold, more new anguiſhes were added to her former griefes, by beholding euen his dead corps not ſpared, but with the wide piercing of a ſpeare wounded then againe, and more then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore lamentably defaced.</p>
               <p>When he was taken downe from his Croſſe, ſo as ſhe might more neerly he hold his wounds, kiſſe, and bath them with her teares, ſorrow ſeemed to be brought neerer to her hart, and his mangled cold body to haue byn buryed therin before it was embalmed, and layd in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher; leauing it when others did, but carrying home with her a liuely, &amp; ſad memory of all his ſufferings, in ſilent and deepe thoughts mournfully reuoluing them; wanting not, whither ſhe
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:18242:65"/>went companions of affliction, &amp; ſorrowes to attend her.</p>
               <p>So as Chriſts mother &amp; friends returning from mount <hi>Caluary</hi> togeather, made a moſt dolefull proceſſion to S. Marks houſe ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnder mount <hi>Syon,</hi> where the B. Virgin waſted with ſorrow, receaued ſuch comforts, as that afficted family of friends could affoard her. And <hi>S. Iohn</hi> not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindful that he had byn adopted her ſonne by his louing mayſter, offered no doubt, with all loue &amp; duty, filiall ſeruices vnto her.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our Sauiours first apparition to his B. Mother.</hi> [Chap. 34.</head>
               <p>ALmighty God is ſaid to wipe away teares from the eyes of his ſeruants; which he doth no otherwiſe, then by manifeſting vnto them obiects of ioy, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:18242:66"/>to the cauſes of their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes; which alſo he performed towards his B. Mother, early in the morning of his glorious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, when according to the multitude, and greatnes of her griefes, he reioyced her hart, with diuine, and vnſpeakable comfort.</p>
               <p>She is noted by holy Authors, not to haue gone with the other deuout women, to embalme her ſonnes Body, as faithfully no doubt perſuaded, that he would riſe againe the third day, as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly he had aſſured her, and confident withall ſo ſoone as he was riſen, to be viſited by him.</p>
               <p>His apparition to her, is not by any Euangeliſt recounted, becauſe a Mothers teſtimony of ſo great a myſtery, might haue by n ſuſpected, and the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of his apparition vnto
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:18242:66"/>her, were ouerhigh withall to be hiſtorically related, eſpecially if learned <hi>Suarez</hi> coniecture there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of be true; that as ſhe had ſadly beheld, and accompanied him in his greateſt humiliations, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions; ſo likewiſe ſhe ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſaw him in his higheſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and contentments, with a double trayne of Angells, and Saintes triumphant, attending him; amongſt whome we may conceaue her gladly to haue ſeene, bodily alſo perchance ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, her beloued pure ſpouſe <hi>S. Joſeph,</hi> her holy Parents likewiſe, &amp; others whome ſhe had knowne before happily diſceaſed: yiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding likewiſe gratefully vnto her amongſt the reſt, as to the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Mother of their Redeemer, due honors and prayſes.</p>
               <p>His fiue greater Woundes in his body ſtill retayned, did ſhine
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:18242:67"/>then as rich Rubyes, by their colour to adorne the louely can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour and tranſparency thereof, and their depth therin did ſhew them to haue byn flowing foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes of graces, for vs once ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned on the Croſſe, and neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne cloſed. The tearings like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of the thornes and whips ſhe ſaw beautifully in him, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly repayred.</p>
               <p>By his louing imbracings he cauſed heauenly languiſhings in her ſoule, &amp; by kiſſes of his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred mouth, he breathed new feruours, and graces into her: &amp; as he appeared firſt after his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection vnto her, ſo was he du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his ſtay on earth, moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently with her.</p>
               <p>Neither had ſhe at any time (as is ſayd of others when he appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto them) the eyes of ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther her body or ſoule reſtrained
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:18242:67"/>from knowing, and delightfully beholding him.</p>
               <p>Finally, as the world from her wombe, by his natiuity, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued him: ſo did he in the day of his Aſcenſion from her armes &amp; imbracements aſcend towards heauen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our B. Ladyes receauing the holy Ghost.</hi> [Chap. 35.</head>
               <p>AMongſt the Apoſtles, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples remaining in <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> expecting, and preparing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to receaue that Diuine Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raclete and Spirit of truth, which our B. Sauiour had promiſed to ſend to them after his Aſcenſion, <hi>S. Luke</hi> affirmes the B. Virgin to haue byn one, ſaying after he had named the Apoſtles; <hi>All theſe were perſouering with one mynd in prayer, with the women, &amp; Mary the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:18242:68"/>Mother</hi> of IESVS; numbring her laſt as the humbleſt amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt them &amp; naming her alone with her ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraygne Title, of the <hi>Mother of Jeſus,</hi> to grace that holy aſſembly the more by the preſence of ſo ſacred a perſon amongſt them.</p>
               <p>That diuine Spirit of loue and goodnes, came to the reſt, firſt with eminent guifts and graces to poſſeſſe them; but he had come to her, twice before, to wit, in the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ception of her ſelfe, &amp; her Son, &amp; was both times abo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly repleniſhed by him. This heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly builder came to rayſe in them as from the ground a heauenly habitation for himſelfe, and the other diuine perſons; but he came to adorne her ſoule as a ſtately pallace already rayſed, and acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed by him.</p>
               <p>This diuine Painter and beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier of ſoules, began only to
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:18242:68"/>draw in them a liuely and loue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly image of their gracious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer; wheras he perfected his former draughts in her, &amp; made her an admirable, and matchles maiſter-peece of heauenly perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>That working fire which Chriſt longed to kindle, and make to flame in the world, according to thoſe his words, <hi>J came to ſend fire into the world &amp;c.</hi> deſcended on the Apoſtles &amp; diſciples, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume thoſe droſſie imperfections for which their mild Lord, had frequently blamed them; but on her, euer pure and cleane, the gracious effects of his diuine preſence were cleere illuſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, inflamed affections, and the higheſt guifts, which for any end he cold beſtow vpon a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>They finally as leſſer veſſells,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:18242:69"/>yet great in reſpect of vs, were ſodainly and happily filled from the flowing ſea of all goodnes; but ſhe who had already contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned within her, the euer full, and flowing fountayne of all graces, was as by a deeper tide, &amp; larger Channell which it bad to runne in, made a full ſea, and a bliſſefull depth of heauenly waters, flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fully into her.</p>
               <p>If any one ſhould curiouſly aske me, what kind of graces were heaped ſo on her? I can only tell him, they were ſuch as in the happy Courſe of her life after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, might be vſefull, and as the Mother of God, ſerue ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to enrich and exalt her.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:18242:69"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the aboad and manner of our B. Ladyes life, after her receauing the holy Ghost.</hi> [Chap. 36.</head>
               <p>S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaking of this ſacred treaſure recommended by his dying Maiſter vnto him, telleth vs, that he <hi>tooke her into his owne:</hi> not that he had any worldly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes to bring her vnto, but that he had a louing care to performe all filiall dutyes vnto her; ſo that, till the Apoſtles diſperſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abroad ſhe liued for the moſt at <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> with him, ſuſtayned by common almes, with other holy widowes, and greatly delighted in her pouerty, as formerly ſhe had byn: where it ioyed her no leſſe to ſee the zealous and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full labours of the Apoſtles, in conuerting ſoules to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of her diuine Sonne, then
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:18242:70"/>it comforted, and edified them all, to behold her humble and examplar conuerſation amongſt them, bleſſing her pure wombe which had miraculouſly concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued their heauenly Redeemer, her Paps which had nurſed him, her Hands which had cloathed him, and the other partes of her louely body, which had byn ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable vnto him. And the more they were illuminated to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the diuine maieſty of their Lord, the more highly they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended her excellency, and with a reuerentiall loue, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly reſpected her.</p>
               <p>Afterwards when <hi>S. John</hi> with the other Apoſtles left <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> he tooke this B. Virgin to <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> with him, (as the Fathers of the firſt Generall Counſell hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den there, traditionally affirmed) where ſhe was no doubt holily
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:18242:70"/>delighted, to behould Iewes and Gentills together with her ſonns graces happily, and equally enri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched; holpen, no doubt, in their firſt conuerſions, and much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created to behould this modell of perfection, and ſecond light, ordayned to ſhine in heauen, conuerſant moſt humbly, and examplarly amongſt them.</p>
               <p>Neither were the holy places of <hi>Palestine</hi> ſo viſited (as ſhe is ſayd to haue byn) by other deuout Chriſtians; repayring thither to behold the mother of their Lord ready with an humble gladnes to welcome them, and to confirme them in their fayth, by relating many myſterious ſpeeches, and paſſages of her ſonnes life, which none, as an eye &amp; eare witneſſe, but her ſelfe, could deliuer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. And eſpecially ſhe is ſayd, ſweetly and frequently to
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:18242:71"/>haue repeated vnto them theſe words of her diuine ſonne, <hi>Be you perfect, as your heauenly Father is perfect.</hi> A high leſſon indeed, and by her fitly taught, who next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heauenly Authour therof practiſed the ſame, and liued ſo long after him for the comfort, &amp; inſtruction of ſuch holy ſoules as were by his Apoſtle (<hi>S. John</hi> eſpecially) conuerted vnto him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladyes manner of prayer.</hi> [Chap. 37.</head>
               <p>PRayer (ſayth <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi>) is as the breathing of holy ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, whereby they draw the pure ayre of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly graces into them. Light &amp; Loue are the chief fruits thereof, and beſt meanes to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the ſame in vs: for Light in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth Loue, and Loue when it is ardent augmenteth that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:18242:71"/>Clarity, wherby it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced; and by mutually inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ech other, both of them grow in holy ſoules to ſuch perfection, as the one is ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome darkned, or the other coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at any tyme ſo but that like Ouens frequently &amp; throughly warmed with new fyres, they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer retayne great warmth, &amp; holy feruour in them.</p>
               <p>Their fancies in ſleep often imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate their Vnderſtanding, and borrow as it were from the rich ſtore-houſes of their memories, holy Obiects, and Diſcourſes, which as heauenly alarums do eaſily waken their wills, &amp; make them interrupt often the repoſe of their ſenſes, by breaking forth into holy aſpiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; as dry wood is with ſlender ſparkles ſoone kindled, and inflamed.</p>
               <p>This great guift of Prayer ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:18242:72"/>in the mother of God, with her other graces, to a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull perfection: ſo as her Soule therein, was with a heauenly ſplendor, next to Beatificall Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity it ſelfe, continually rayſed; and her Loue naturall and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall, to her God and Sonne, like two fiery wings, mounted her thoughts &amp; affections more &amp; more towards him, by whome they were inflamed.</p>
               <p>An immaculate innocency of life added a moſt gracious ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to this riſing rod of all hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly perfums and ſpices ſweetly compoſed. Humility rayſed it, a pure Intention made way for it, and a conſtant perſeuerance ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in did ſurely obtayne what by her prayer ſhe intended.</p>
               <p>The high Attributes of God, and the ſacred myſteries of her ſonnes life and death, ſtill conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:18242:72"/>in her memory, and confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in her hart, as the Euangeliſt twice telleth vs, were the vſuall ſubiects therof; &amp; her diſcourſes therein, were free from all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of diſtractions, and by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly illuminations cleared ſo, as like Eagles mounted to their high pitch aboue the cloudes, ſhe ſoared with little labour, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came in them, euer ſweetly, and diuinely inflamed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the wonderfull merit of our B. Ladyes actions.</hi> [Chap. 38.</head>
               <p>LEarned <hi>Suarez</hi> writing of this fubiect, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> certaine groundes of fayth and Philoſophy, gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſo ſtrong a concluſion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the B. Virgins wonderfull manner of meriting, and redou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, by ech act, her former graces, as he dared not to publiſh
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:18242:73"/>his doctrine, vntill the learned Diuines of <hi>Spayne,</hi> had with their opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s approued it. The ſumme of his diſcourſe is this.</p>
               <p>As naturall habits are produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by naturall acts, when they are intenſe and perfect; ſo ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall habits are by the diuine infuſer of them, conferred on ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſoules, according to the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of thoſe ſupernaturall acts, wherby holy ſoules merit an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of them. Wherefore ſince the B. Virgin, did in ech holy act done by her, cooperate with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer graces giuen her, fully, and according to their whole inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as hauing no ſinfull inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to hinder her: ſo did ſhe ſtill merit, according to the full in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion &amp; perfection of her acts, to haue new graces infuſed into her, and conſequently to haue former graces redoubled, by ech
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:18242:73"/>one of them; ſo that ſhe heaped in her ſoule hourely, treaſures of merits, and by them in the end of her life arriued to an immenſity of graces.</p>
               <p>Sinfull Ignorance did neuer darken her illuminated ſoule, Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour ſeduce, or Malice corrupt her. Senſe neuer rebelled againſt Reaſon; and Concupiſcence the roote of ſinne, was according to <hi>S. Thomas</hi> euer kept from grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and totally at length extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed in her. Wherby this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly <hi>Sulamite,</hi> became ordered in all vertues ſo, as a high Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom guided them in their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall operations, &amp; Charity com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded them; wherby ſhe came, as weighty things remayne in their Center, to be in them im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueably fixed.</p>
               <p>Pride did at no tyme rayſe her, or Puſillanimity deiect her. Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18242:74"/>did not perturbe her, or ſenſuall Appetites diſorder her. Sanctity did cleare, like a rich pearle, her gracious grouth; and an Angelicall Purity of mind and body, did for her diuine ſpouſe conſecrate &amp; ſpotleſly conſerue her. Humility to conclude, made her ponderous in all actions, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience rounded her, and other graces ſmoothed her, in ſuch ſort, as finally ſhe became in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a rare, and matchleſſe vnion of Created Perfection, doing all her actions in the ſubſtance, and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of them, ſo, as it is a Catholique point of faith to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue, ſhe neuer offended, by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, or commiſſion venially in them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladies Sacramentall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces heere gayned.</hi> [Chap. 39.</head>
               <p>GReat Authors (<hi>S. Clement</hi> and others) haue affirmed our B.
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:18242:74"/>Sauiour himſelfe to haue bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed his Mother, aſwell to bewti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy her ſoule by the faireſt chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of that Sacrament, as to take an occaſion therby, beſides the wonderfull merit of her owne actions, to heape in his owne bounty, on her ſoule, vnconcea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable graces.</p>
               <p>The deſcenſion of the Holy Ghoſt vpon her in the day of Pentecoſt, was as an eminent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and Confirmation of her graces therein receaued, and the moſt holy ſacrifice, &amp; ſacrament of her ſonnes body &amp; bloud dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with other Chriſtians recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, was as an euer-full, and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fountayne of heauenly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings running into her.</p>
               <p>Her oblation thereof in the Apoſtles hands, &amp; preparation to receaue it, was ſuitable (no doubt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) to the immenfity of
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:18242:75"/>actuall and habituall graces in her ſoule: their Clarity did illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate her, their Feruour inflame her, Humility proſtrated her, Piety diſpoſed her, &amp; faith made her ſo firmely to belieue her ſonnes glorious, albeit inuiſible, preſence therein, as if ſhe had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently beheld him; humbly thanking him in behalfe of her ſelfe, and vs alſo, for that ſecond annihilating, as it were of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, to communicate the fruites of his paſſion to faithfull ſoules worthily receauing him; fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently enioying glimſes almoſt of beatificall Clarity it ſelfe, as often as ſhe ſacramentally recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him; he recompencing ſo, in a ſorte, the wonted, and deſired Comforts of his viſible prefence with her.</p>
               <p>And if <hi>S. Mary Magdalen</hi> in her holy retyrement neere <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſills</hi>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:18242:75"/>in <hi>France,</hi> had bodily rapts, Angelicall viſits, heauenly melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and greater fauours, by her louing and beloued Lord, daily affoarded her; can we reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly doubt, but that in higher &amp; more delightfull manners he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed his loue to her, graciou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly aboue all Creatures indeared vnto him?</p>
               <p>Or do ſo many authenticall &amp; vndoubted hiſtories mention his glorious apparitions to other Saintes, men and woomen, for yielding them, yet aliue, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar comforts, and inſtructions; and may we not iuſtly conceaue him to haue byn more open-han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and liberall, in ſhewing his loue to her, who beſt deſerued ſuch fauours, and had as a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Mother, from a louing Sonne, moſt right to receaue them?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="chapter">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:18242:76"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladies death.</hi> [Chap 40.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAint Denis</hi> not conuerted by <hi>S. Paul</hi> at <hi>Athens</hi> before the 16. yeare after our Sauiours Paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (as <hi>Baronius,</hi> with <hi>Suarez,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great Authors haue colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted) &amp; writing as he doth of his hauing byn at <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> with <hi>S. Peter, S. Iohn</hi> and others aſwell A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles as chiefe diſciples of our Sauiour, at the death and funeral of this ſacred Virgin, conuinceth her to haue liued well nigh 20. yeares after her Sonnes paſſion, to gayne no doubt a lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; happy harueſt of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly merits for her ſelfe, to comfort likewiſe the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles themſelues in their holy labours, and to edify others by them conuerted by her gracefull perſon, exemplar life, &amp; conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation amongſt them.</p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:18242:76"/>
               <p> Her happy end may be thought to haue byn prophetically reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the Apoſtles, and diſciples, that beſides their mutuall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of ſeeing ech other, they might alſo enioy ſo contentfull a bleſſing, as to be hould the ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full paſſage of this ſacred Mother to her diuine Sonne, take their laſt leaue of her, heere in this world, and celebrate her fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls with due loue and venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>The ſicknes wherof ſhe dyed may be thought to haue byn a rauiſhing exceſſe and ſweet lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhment of heauenly loue, and longinging to haſten to her ſonne, calling her vnto him, <hi>Come my beloued from Libanus, thou shalt be crowned:</hi> which freely yielded vnto by her, might cauſe ſuch a concurrence of vitall ſpirits, to rayſe the thoughts and affections
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:18242:77"/>of her ſoule, as they failed, to conſerue a needfull diſpoſition for life, in her bodily members and ſenſes.</p>
               <p>So as lying ſweetly repoſed on her bed, with all the Apoſtles, &amp; many chiefe Diſciples of her Sonne kneeling about her, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing newly before, for a happy <hi>viaticum</hi> to heauen moſt deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely receaued him, whom firſt in her wombe, ſhe had diuinely conceaued, with an vnexpreſsible ardour of loue, giuing her bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and farewell to all preſent, ſhe breathed out her gracious ſoule into her Sonnes hands, there preſent to receaue it, waited on by the moſt glorious Princes of his Court, gladly attending him their Lord, and her his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued Mother, in their triumpha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t proceſsion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="chapter">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:18242:77"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladies Aſſumption.</hi> [Chap. 41.</head>
               <p>PIous eares, and harts worthily abhorre to heare ſpoken, that corruption (ſayth <hi>S. John Damaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene</hi>) inuaded, and wormes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured that ſacred fleſh, a part whereof the Author himſelfe of immortality had aſſumed: or that this ſtately branch of <hi>Ieſſes</hi> root, euer rotted in the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, whoſe flowre was in Heauen ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly ripened: or finally that this louely Tabernacle of the Higheſt became in the bewtifull frame therof, after death, vtterly diſſolued.</p>
               <p>No ſurely, as the ſame had byn whilſt it was aliue, many wayes graced by her diuine ſonne: ſo was it, being dead from loathſomneſſe, and corruption
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:18242:78"/>totally preſerued, as for many reaſons it was fitting. Firſt, in that it had not byn with ſinne originally infected, as other bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are, when ſoules void of grace are firſt vnited vnto them. Secondly for that it was euer a moſt pure habitation of her gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſoule, neuer by it actually defiled, or viciouſly inclined. Thirdly, becauſe it had byn the ſubiect of heauenly wonders for her Creatours glory, and mans eternall ſaluation, wrought hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily in it; and ech part thereof made ſacred, by immediate tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and ſeruices done to the Eternall Word Incarnate within it, and nurſed by it.</p>
               <p>Her wombe for example was (as the Spouſe, for the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full purity, and fertility thereof, calleth it in the Canticles) a Heape of heauenly Grayne, to
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:18242:78"/>nouriſh ſoules eternally, with lillyes inuironed: a pure Neſt, wherein the celeſtiall <hi>Phaenix,</hi> and Birde of Diuine Loue was hatched: the Tyring-houſe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſonne of God was for high ends humanely diſguiſed; finally a Bed-chamber, richly prepared for the celeſtiall Bride, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come therin, to our nature firſt, and to all holy ſoules afterwards, eternally eſpouſed.</p>
               <p>Her ſacred breaſts, were as two Pearly-bottels, tipped with rich rubies, and filled once from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, ſweetly to nurſe him, by whome (as the Church ſingeth in her Office) birds are fed, and all Creatures ſuſtayned.</p>
               <p>Her lappe was as an eaſy Couch wherein the ſonne of God lay neere to her louing hart content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully repoſed.</p>
               <p>Her armes and hands had byn
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:18242:79"/>for many yeares togeather, holy inſtruments fitly made and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, to imbrace, and ſerue him.</p>
               <p>Her lipps were as two Ruby gates, at which her ſoule and her diuine ſonnes had often met, &amp; parlied with mutuall ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of loue, and new breathings from him of heauenly graces in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her.</p>
               <p>Her eyes had byn as cleare windowes, for her ſoule, delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to behould, for 33. yeares togeather, his corporall bewtyes and deepely to imprint in her hart a liuely, and louely image of him.</p>
               <p>To conclude, all other parts of her virginall pure body, for ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable acts done to the omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent Authour therof, were by him after her death, highly reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected (no doubt) gloriouſly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, and wonderfully exalted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="chapter">
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:18242:79"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the glory of our</hi> B. <hi>Lady aſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted.</hi> [Chap 42.</head>
               <p>HEr ſepulcher is ſayd to haue byn placed in the garden of <hi>Gethſemani,</hi> wherein by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and other chiefe diſciples of her Sonne, her body was ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnely and deuoutly intombed. And as flowers do ſmell ſweetly in their firſt buddings; ſo this fayre flower, about to open it ſelf in its immortall beauty, yielded to all preſent a heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly fragran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy (as <hi>S. Iohn Damaſcene</hi> from A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall tradition recounteth) and ſweetned that ſtony recepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, and part of the earth, whence it was ſoone after into her ſons heauenly garden, to be gloriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tranſplanted.</p>
               <p>So that when the Apoſtolicall intombers thereof had left it,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:18242:80"/>Angelical ſpirits, as a ſacred trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſerued it, &amp; atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the third day, when it was by their Lord, and her Sonne ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully rayſed, and with ſuch a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious change, as thoſe celeſtiall Princes wondred to ſee agayne in her, as before they had ſeene in their Lord, a clodd of earth ſo curiouſly molded, &amp; graciouſly transformed, asking ech other, not as ignorant who ſhe was, but admiring her greatnes: <hi>Who is she that aſcendeth from the deſert, in delights, leaning on her beloued?</hi> Delights indeed <hi>(ſayth S. Bernard)</hi> abounding in her, and flowing ſtill in earth and in heauen gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly from her, which can be no more expreſſed, then her glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries deſcribed: ſuitable no doubt to the graces of her ſoule, &amp; ſuch (ſayth he) as well beſeemed ſo diuine a ſonne to beſtow vpon
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:18242:80"/>ſo deſeruing a mother.</p>
               <p>His heauenly Father was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe openha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded at the ſame tyme in heaping gratious fauours on her, who had byn Mother of his eternall ſonne, and ioint-parent with himſelfe of him, &amp; the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt was effuſed no doubt in his bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty then to her, whom here on earth he had ſingularly eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to himſelfe, and made mother of a diuine child, firſt from him (ſaith <hi>S. Leo</hi>) in her ſoule, and afterwards in her wombe moſt graciouſly conceaued.</p>
               <p>And as they had rayſed her in the holy merits of her life far a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all Creatures: ſo was ſhe at her entrance into heauen highly in throned, and ſupremely exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="chapter">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:18242:81"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladyes Coronation.</hi> [Chap. 43.</head>
               <p>THe Diademe with which this Queene of Heauen was crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by her ſonne, at her glorious entrance into his Kingdome, was in the riches thereof, ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble (no doubt) to her wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full merits, and graced with twelue ſuch Starrs, as adorned the head of that myſterious wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man mentioned in the Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyps, importing twelue peculiar Graces, conferred by the diuine Perſons on her.</p>
               <p>The firſt of them was, her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall dignity, and office of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the eternall word incarnate within her, wherby ſhe came to haue a ſingular neerenes, and dearenes vnto him.</p>
               <p>The 2. was, her immaculate
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:18242:82"/>conception, happily therein be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning a rich harueſt of heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly merits, brought out of her mothers wombe into the world with her.</p>
               <p>The 3. was, her preſeruation from venially offending after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, wherby ſhe alone of all Adams naturall children equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Angells themſelues, in the vnſpotted innocency of her life, as in the graces of her ſoule, ſhe incomparably excelled them.</p>
               <p>The 4. added an Excellency to the former, &amp; arriued to the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieſt effect of originall iuſtice it<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelf, which was to feele no Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence, or rebellion at all in her members &amp; ſenſes, but to haue nature and grace euer in her, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniouſly compoſed.</p>
               <p>The 5. was, her virginall vow of Purity, wherby ſhe conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted herſelfe to her Heauenly
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:18242:83"/>ſpouſe; and before the Ghoſpell of her ſonne, in this, and other graces arriued to the higheſt top of Euangelicall perfection.</p>
               <p>To 6. was, the pure Conce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, and manner of her ſonnes Natiuity, a Priuiledge indeed (ſayth <hi>S. Bernard</hi>) for Gods mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alone graciouſly reſerued.</p>
               <p>The 7. was, her hauing beſides Fayth, and continuall Illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of heauenly Graces, in a moſt affectuous cleare manner, an experimentall knowledge of many chiefe myſteries of faith wrought by her Sonne; ſo as her ſelfe was with him an actour alſo in them, as his miraculous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, Natiuity &amp;c. happily ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to illminate &amp; inflame her.</p>
               <p>The 9. was, naturall &amp; ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall loue towards him, as to her God and ſonne ſweetly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned, &amp; like two fiery wings,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:18242:83"/>ray ſing her ſoule inceſſantly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him.</p>
               <p>The 9. was, her life led for 30. yeares &amp; more, inſeparably with him, affording her hourely occaſions of doing motherly ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices immediately vnto him.</p>
               <p>The 10. was, her great ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringes for him, &amp; martyrdome finally with him, cauſed by Loue, making his wounds &amp; torments her own by a moſt tender Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion.</p>
               <p>The 11. was, her happy end, graced by the Apoſtles preſent thereat, and much more highly honoured by her Sonnes perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall readines to receaue her bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Soule, reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended vnto him.</p>
               <p>The 12. was her bodily Aſſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption after death, wherby ſhe preuented the rayſing of other Saints bodies in the generall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and came to be with a
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18242:84"/>complete fulnes of bleſſed ioyes, eternally poſſeſſed.</p>
               <p>Where I leaue thee (O ſacred Virgin, and gracious Mother of my heauenly Redeemer) in the bright Noone of thy glorious Clarity neuer ſetting; in the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of thy loue euer flaming; and in the flowing of thy delights neuer ebbing, but increaſing ſtill; ſo as holpen by thy powerfull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion, I hope, albeit a farre of as men gaze on the ſtarres, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould thee on a ſtately Throne, neere thy ſonnes right hand glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly exalted: purpoſing in the meane tyme during my mortall and miſerable life, in all I may, next to thy diuine ſonne, my Lord and Sauiour himſelfe, to honour and ſerue thee.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18242:81" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>FASCICVLVS MYRRHAE.</p>
            <p>OR A briefe Treatiſe of our Lord and Sauiours Paſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by the R. Fa. I. F. of the Society of JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Permiſſu Superiorum. 1633.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:18242:82"/>
            <list>
               <item>Chap. XVII. <hi>Of our Sauiours third ſpeach vttered on the Croſſe, to the good Theefe pag.</hi> 92.</item>
               <item>Chap. XVIII. <hi>Of our Sauiours mysterious ſilence on the Croſse for three houres togeather. pa.</hi> 98.</item>
               <item>Chap. XIX. <hi>Of our Sauiours Fourth ſpeach on the Croſſe. pag.</hi> 104.</item>
               <item>Chap. XX. <hi>Of our Sauiours fifth word vttered the Croſſe, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his thirst. pag.</hi> 109.</item>
               <item>Chap. XXI. <hi>Of our Sauiours ſixt Word on his Croſſe,</hi> It is conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated. <hi>pag.</hi> 113.</item>
               <item>Chap. XXII. <hi>Of our Sauiours last cry, and death. pag. 118.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap XXIII. <hi>Of the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of our Sauiours death, &amp; opening of his ſide. pag. 122.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. XXIV. <hi>Of our Sauiours Buriall. pag. 126.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:18242:84"/>
            <head>THE TABLE OF CHAPTERS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>CHap. I. <hi>Of our Bleſſed Ladyes high, &amp; holy Pedigree.</hi> pag. 1.</item>
               <item>Chap. II. <hi>Of our <hi>B.</hi> Ladyes imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate Conception.</hi> 4.</item>
               <item>Chap. III. <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladyes Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity.</hi> 9.</item>
               <item>Chap. IV. <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladies Preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, &amp; life in the Temple.</hi> 12.</item>
               <item>Chap. V. <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladyes Eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalls to S. Ioſeph.</hi> 14.</item>
               <item>Chap. VI. <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladyes ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the Angell.</hi> 18.</item>
               <item>Chap. VII. <hi>Of the Eternall Word in her Bleſſed wombe.</hi> 22.</item>
               <item>Chap. VIII. <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladyes viſit of S.</hi> Elizabeth. 25.</item>
               <item>Chap. IX. <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladyes Canti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, &amp; ſtay with</hi> S. Elizabeth. 28.</item>
               <item>Chap. X. <hi>Of our Sauiours Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion manifested to</hi> S. Ioſeph. 32.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:18242:85"/>
               <item>Chap. XI. <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladies Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the byrth of her Child.</hi> 36.</item>
               <item>Chap. XII. <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladies iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to Bethleem.</hi> 39.</item>
               <item>Chap. XIII. <hi>Of our Bleſſed Ladies Child-birth.</hi> 41.</item>
               <item>Chap. XIV. <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladies inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning the shepheards.</hi> 44.</item>
               <item>Chap. XV. <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladies nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, &amp; ſeruing her diuine Son.</hi> 48.</item>
               <item>Chap. XVI. <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladyes ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in her ſonnes Circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſion.</hi> 50.</item>
               <item>Chap. XVII. <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladyes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the Name of</hi> IESVS. 53.</item>
               <item>Chap. XVIII. <hi>Of the Sages finding the Child with the B. Mother.</hi> 56.</item>
               <item>Chap. XIX. <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladies Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification.</hi> 59.</item>
               <item>Chap. XX. <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladies flight with her Child into Egypt.</hi> 63.</item>
               <item>Chap. XXI. <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladyes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne with her Child thence.</hi> 66.</item>
               <item>Chap. XXII. <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladies fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her Sonne in the Temple.</hi> 71.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:18242:85"/>
               <item>Chap. XXIII. <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladies life after her Sonnes Baptiſme.</hi> 75.</item>
               <item>Chap. XXIV. <hi>Of the</hi> B. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgins ſorrow for</hi> S. Ioſephs <hi>death.</hi> 79.</item>
               <item>Chap. XXV. <hi>Of her being in</hi> Cana <hi>with her ſonne at a wedding.</hi> 83.</item>
               <item>Chap. XXVI. <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladies liuing at</hi> Capharnaum. 86.</item>
               <item>Chap. XXVII. <hi>Of the woman bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be of the B <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin.</hi> 89.</item>
               <item>Chap. XXVIII. <hi>Of our</hi> B <hi>Ladyes expecting her Sonne, at a doore in</hi> Capharnaum. <hi>Math. 12.</hi> 92.</item>
               <item>Chap. XXIX. <hi>Of our Bleſſed La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſuffering with her ſonne.</hi> 96.</item>
               <item>Chap. XXX. <hi>Of our B. Ladyes ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king leaue of her Sonne.</hi> 99.</item>
               <item>Chap. XXXI. <hi>Of our B. Ladies ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall griefes in her Sonnes paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> 103.</item>
               <item>Chap. XXXII. <hi>Of Christs ſpeach to his mother.</hi> 106.</item>
               <item>Chap. XXXIII. <hi>Of our B. Ladies particular ſorrow in the death,
<pb facs="tcp:18242:86"/>and buriall of her Sonne.</hi> 109.</item>
               <item>Chap. XXXIV. <hi>Of our Sauiours first apparition to his Mother.</hi> 111.</item>
               <item>Chap. XXXV. <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladyes receauing the holy Ghost.</hi> 115.</item>
               <item>Chap. XXXVI. <hi>Of the aboad, and manner of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladyes life, after her receauing the holy Ghost.</hi> 119.</item>
               <item>Chap. XXXVII. <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladyes manner of prayer.</hi> 122.</item>
               <item>Chap. XXXVIII. <hi>Of the wonderfull merit of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladyes actions.</hi> 125.</item>
               <item>Cha. XXXIX. <hi>Of our B. Ladies Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tall graces heere gayned.</hi> 128.</item>
               <item>Ch. XL. <hi>Of our</hi> B. <hi>Ladies death.</hi> 132.</item>
               <item>Chap. XLI. <hi>Of our B. Ladies Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</hi> 135.</item>
               <item>Chap. XLII. <hi>Of the glory of our</hi> B. <hi>Lady aſſumpted.</hi> 139.</item>
               <item>Chap. XLIII. <hi>Of our B. Ladyes Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation.</hi> 142.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18242:86"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
